m 20 0 l 209 0 b 218 0 229 11 229 20 l 229 209 b 229 218 218 228 209 228 l 20 228 b 11 228 0 218 0 209 l 0 20 b 0 11 11 0 20 0
m 115 64 l 115 35 l 171 0 l 177 0 l 133 46 l 143 52 l 179 0 l 184 0 l 159 63 l 229 107 l 229 182 l 145 96 l 135 122 l 207 227 l 137 227 l 115 172 l 115 93 l 126 76 l 115 64 l 104 76 l 115 93 l 115 172 l 93 227 l 23 227 l 95 122 l 84 96 l 0 182 l 0 107 l 70 63 l 45 0 l 50 0 l 87 52 l 97 46 l 52 0 l 59 0 l 115 35
m 71 60 b 71 0 161 0 161 60 b 161 120 71 120 71 60
m 325 0 l 355 0 l 332 47 l 354 47 l 399 136 l 369 136 l 328 53 l 288 136 l 257 136 l 325 0 m 467 0 l 497 0 l 474 47 l 496 47 l 541 136 l 511 136 l 470 53 l 430 136 l 399 136 l 467 0 m 545 1 l 583 1 l 583 14 l 568 14 l 568 19 l 583 19 l 583 30 l 568 30 l 568 34 l 599 34 l 599 30 l 583 30 l 583 19 l 599 19 l 599 14 l 583 14 l 583 1 l 611 1 b 616 1 622 6 622 10 l 622 36 l 652 0 l 678 0 l 644 41 l 622 41 l 622 47 l 596 47 l 597 54 l 625 54 l 625 68 l 541 68 l 541 54 l 572 54 l 571 47 l 545 47 l 545 1 m 583 72 l 583 85 l 569 85 l 569 90 l 598 90 l 598 85 l 583 85 l 583 72 l 611 72 b 615 72 621 78 621 82 l 653 44 l 678 44 l 644 86 l 621 86 l 621 103 l 597 103 l 597 136 l 570 136 l 564 126 l 562 136 l 542 136 l 548 107 l 568 107 l 565 121 l 571 121 l 571 103 l 547 103 l 547 72 l 583 72 m 600 107 l 620 107 l 624 124 l 653 89 l 679 89 l 642 136 l 615 136 l 618 132 l 606 132 l 600 107 m 689 0 l 716 0 l 721 15 l 732 15 l 732 30 l 718 56 l 731 56 l 735 100 l 721 100 l 717 59 l 714 64 l 714 136 l 693 136 l 693 79 l 676 79 l 707 30 l 679 30 l 679 15 l 694 15 l 689 0 m 738 0 l 804 0 b 807 0 813 6 813 9 l 813 87 l 794 87 l 794 14 l 756 14 l 756 87 l 763 77 l 763 21 l 787 21 l 787 91 l 798 91 l 798 120 l 820 120 l 812 136 l 778 136 l 778 90 l 748 136 l 723 136 l 756 87 l 738 87 l 738 0 m 257 151 l 275 151 l 297 182 l 319 151 l 337 151 l 304 197 l 304 227 l 290 227 l 290 197 l 257 151 m 337 151 l 355 151 l 377 182 l 399 151 l 417 151 l 384 197 l 384 227 l 370 227 l 370 197 l 337 151 m 425 192 l 447 192 b 445 181 427 181 425 192 l 410 192 b 414 162 458 162 462 192 l 462 206 l 425 206 b 425 210 429 212 433 213 l 462 213 l 462 227 l 433 227 b 412 227 408 203 410 192 m 462 151 l 532 151 l 532 165 l 504 165 l 504 227 l 489 227 l 489 165 l 462 165 l 462 151 m 580 172 l 580 186 l 549 186 b 543 186 543 192 549 192 l 565 192 b 589 192 589 227 565 227 l 532 227 l 532 213 l 565 213 b 570 213 570 206 565 206 l 549 206 b 524 206 524 172 549 172 l 580 172 m 592 213 l 606 213 l 606 227 l 592 227 l 592 213 m 639 172 l 665 172 l 665 186 l 639 186 b 623 186 623 213 639 213 l 665 213 l 665 227 l 639 227 b 603 227 603 172 639 172 m 700 184 b 722 184 722 215 700 215 l 700 229 b 740 229 740 170 700 170 b 660 170 660 229 700 229 l 700 215 b 680 215 680 184 700 184 m 737 172 l 782 172 b 803 172 813 177 813 198 l 813 228 l 799 228 l 799 198 b 799 186 793 187 782 187 l 782 228 l 768 228 l 768 187 l 752 187 l 752 228 l 737 228 l 737 172
人人影视
YYeTs.com
原创翻译 双语字幕
■
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
更多影视更新
请登陆www.YYeTs.com
翻译：ntexplorer  薄荷小瑾  ponyonyo  jellobird
翻译：any沫沫  cheeseflower  borat  脸盆王子
■
校对：麦克杜杜格  somehacker    后期：Sung1219
在我年纪尚轻  涉世未深的时候
In my younger and more vulnerable years,
父亲曾这样告诫我
my father gave me some advice.
"多发掘他人身上的闪光点"
"Always try to see the best in people," he would say.
父亲的教诲使我不对他人妄加评判
As a consequence, I'm inclined to reserve all judgments.
但我的忍耐也是有限度的
But even I have a limit.
那时  我们每天都醉生梦死
Back then, all of us drank too much.
越是与时俱进
The more in tune with the times we were,
越是长醉不醒
the more we drank.
我们也越是陈旧迂腐
And none of us contributed anything new.
帕金斯疗养院
我从纽约回来时  心中深感厌恶
When I came back from New York, I was disgusted.
我明白  卡罗威先生
I see, Mr. Carraway.
对周围所有的人和事感到厌恶无比
Disgusted with everyone and everything.
帕金斯疗养院  精神康复诊所
病人姓名  尼克·卡罗威  体检结果  酗酒过度  失眠  易怒  焦虑
除了一个人之外
Only one man was exempt from my disgust.
一个人
One man?
卡罗威先生
Mr. Carraway?
盖茨比
Gatsby.
医嘱  1929年12月1日  初次问诊  盖茨比
他是你的朋友吗
Was he a friend of yours?
他是我见过的最乐观的人
He was the single most hopeful person I've ever met.
而且是绝无仅有的
And am ever likely to meet again.
他对周围发生的事十分敏感
There was something about him, a sensitivity.
就像
He was like,
就像一台地震仪
he was like one of those machines
能探测到万里之外的地震
that register earthquakes 10,000 miles away.
你是怎么认识他的
Where'd you meet him?
在纽约的
At a, at a party
派对上认识的
in New York.
那是1922年夏天
In the summer of 1922,
城市发展的脚步越来越快
the tempo of the city approached.
几近疯狂
Hysteria.
股价暴涨至史上最高点
Stocks reached record peaks,
华尔街在呼啸而来的金融大潮中一派昌盛
and Wall Street boomed in a steady golden roar.
派对排场越发奢华
The parties were bigger.
秀场演出越发气派
The shows were broader.
摩天大楼直冲云霄
The buildings were higher.
道德底线逐渐沦丧
The morals were looser,
禁酒令反而使私酒泛滥
and the ban on alcohol had backfired
越演越烈
making the liquor cheaper.
华尔街吸引着充满野心的年轻人
Wall Street was luring the young and ambitious.
我就是其中之一
And I was one of them.
我在距市区20英里的长岛租了一间房子
I rented a house 20 miles from the city on Long Island.
我住在西卵区
I lived at West Egg
一栋无人修葺的小别墅里
in a forgotten groundskeeper's cottage,
被暴发户们的豪宅包围
squeezed among the mansions of the newly rich.
为了尽快上手  我买了一整套
To get started, I bought a dozen volumes
有关信贷  金融和投资的书籍
on credit, banking and investments.
我对此一窍不通
All new to me.
股市再创新高
The stock market hit another high.
大盘持续走高
The market's moving up, up, up!
不过凡事都有风险
Well, of course, nothing is 100 percent.
换我就不会孤注一掷
I wouldn't go investing every penny.
《尤利西斯》
在耶鲁大学时我曾梦想当一名作家
At Yale I dreamed of being a writer
不过最终彻底放弃
but I gave all that up.
在炎炎夏日与繁盛的树荫下
With the sun shining and the great bursts of leaves on the trees,
我本打算在学习中度过整个夏天
I planned to spend the summer studying.
第一章  市场投资
计划未能如愿  却也是件好事
And I probably would have were it not,
因为我那素未谋面的邻居盖茨比
for the riotous amusements that beckoned
在他那巨大城堡内举办的盛大派对
from beyond the walls of that colossal castle
已经勾走了我的魂
owned by a gentleman I had not yet met named Gatsby.
那他是你的邻居了
So, he was your neighbor.
我的邻居  是的
My neighbor. Yeah.
仔细想想  那个难忘的夏季起始于
When I think about it, the history of the summer really began
我驱车去表妹黛西家吃晚餐的那一夜
the night I drove over to my cousin Daisy's for dinner.
她住在对岸东卵区
She lived across the bay in old moneyed,
一座祖传庭院里
East Egg.
她丈夫是美国最富有的家族之一的继承人
Her husband was heir to one of America's wealthiest families.
他的名字叫汤姆·布坎南
His name was Tom Buchanan.
我们就读于耶鲁时  他还是个运动健将
When we were at Yale together, he'd been a sporting star.
但那些都是英雄往事了
But now his glory days were behind him
他现在安于...
and he contented himself with...
您的电话  布坎南先生
Telephone, Monsieur Buchanan.
-是我  -一些风流韵事
- It's me. - other affairs.
不是告诉过你别打到这儿来吗
I thought I told you not to call me here.
波阿斯
Boaz!
波阿斯是《圣经》中的富豪  莎士比亚是人尽皆知的文豪
莎士比亚
Shakespeare!
汤姆
Tom!
你那本伟大的美国小说写得怎样了
How's the great American novel coming?
我最近在沃尔特·切斯的公司卖证券呢
I'm selling bonds with Walter Chase's outfit.
晚饭后和我一起去镇上
Let's say after dinner, you and I, we go into town.
-不行  -带你去见见老弟兄
- I can't. - Catch up with the old wolf pack.
-明天还上班  -废话  让你去就去
- Big day on the job tomorrow. - Nonsense! We're going.
全美第一
First team, all-American.
看见没
You see?
造就了今天的我
Made me who I am today.
森林山[纽约长岛赛场]
Forest Hills.
大败威尔士亲王队那帮娘娘腔
Played the Prince of Wales. What a sissy.
人得靠自己本事活着  尼克
Life is something you dominate, Nick.
只要你有一技之长
If you're any good.
亨利
Henri!
你在哪儿呢
Where are you?
这几扇门
The doors.
给我关上
Close them.
-抱歉  -谢谢
- Sorry. - Thank you.
是你吗  亲爱的
Is that you, my lovely?
黛西·布坎南  绝代佳人
Daisy Buchanan, the golden girl.
她散发着一股令人窒息的热情
A breathless warmth flowed from her.
仿佛在这世上除你之外
A promise that there was no one else
她谁也不想见
in the world she so wanted to see.
芝加哥那些人想我了吗
Do they miss me in Chicago?
是的  不少人托我带个好
Yes. Um, at least a dozen people send their love.
真不错
How gorgeous.
没有你的日子他们悲痛欲绝
They're absolutely in mourning.
-他们愁眉苦脸  真的  -瞎说
- They're crying. Yes. - No.
-才不信你  -抱头痛哭
- I don't believe you. - Wailing.
-我才不信你呢  -仰天长啸
- I don't believe you. - They're screaming.
"黛西·布坎南  没有你我们活不了"
"Daisy Buchanan, we can't live without you!"
我高兴死了
I'm paralyzed with happiness.
乔丹·贝克  著名高尔夫球手
Jordan Baker. A very famous golfer.
《纽约闲谈》
她是我见过的最让人手足无措的人
She was the most frightening person I'd ever seen.
我在《运动人生》的封面上见过你的照片
Well, I've seen your face on the cover of Sporting Life.
尼克·卡罗威
Nick Carraway.
但能注视着她仍是一桩美差
But I enjoyed looking at her.
我在沙发上躺得太久了
I've been lying on that sofa for as long as I can remember.
这个夏天我要把你俩撮合到一块去
This summer I'll fling you two together.
我会让你们盛装打扮
I'll push you into linen closets,
然后一起出海游玩
and out to sea in boats!
-想得美  -对了  尼克
- I'm not listening to a word. - So, Nick,
黛西说你住在西卵区那边
Daisy tells me that you're over in West Egg throwing your lot in
和那些攀高结贵的暴发户们住一起
with those social-climbing primitive new-money types.
我不过租了间每月80块的陋居罢了
My little shack's just a cardboard box at 80 a month.
你过得真有意思
Your life is adorable.
我倒是认识一个西卵区的人
I know somebody in West Egg.
我和那边的人还没来往过呢
I don't know a single person that side of the bay.
但你一定听说过盖茨比
You must know Gatsby.
盖茨比
Gatsby?
哪个盖茨比
What Gatsby?
夫人  晚膳已备齐
Madame, the dinner is servi.
想听听咱家的秘密吗
Would you like to hear a family secret?
-洗耳恭听  -是有关管家的鼻子的
- That's why I came over. - It's about the butler's nose.
事情变得每况愈下
Things went from bad to worse.
我不喜欢"大老粗"这个词
I hate that word "Hulking."
尼克  听说你准备娶一个
Nicky, I heard a rumor that you were getting married
-西卵区的姑娘  -哪有的事
- to a girl out West. - It's a libel.
我没钱啊
I'm too poor.
除非找个老女人准备坐吃遗产
They have to be old so they die quickly.
咱换个话题行吗
Can't we talk about something else?
什么都好  谈谈作物收成吧
Anything. Crops.
你让我觉得自己像野蛮人  黛西
You're making me feel uncivilized, Daisy.
文明已经要四分五裂了
Civilization's going to pieces.
你读过戈达德写的那本
Have you read The Rise of the Colored Empires
《黑色帝国的崛起》吗
by this fellow Goddard?
人们都该读读这本书
Everybody ought to read it.
如果白人再掉以轻心的话
The idea is that it's up to us, the dominant race to watch out
别的种族就要主宰一切了
or these other races will have control of things.
汤姆近来看问题比较长远
Tom's very profound lately.
他读了很多晦涩难懂的书籍
He reads deep books with long words in them.
这是有根据的
It's been proved.
是科学的道理
It's scientific.
我们得消灭这些苗头
We've got to beat them down.
布坎南府邸
Buchanan residence.
是汽车修理厂的威尔逊先生打来的
Monsieur Wilson, from the garage.
布坎南先生
Monsieur Buchanan.
不好意思  我去去就来
Excuse me, I'll be right back.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
你提到的这个盖茨比先生
Well, this Mr. Gatsby you spoke of,
-他就住我隔壁  -嘘  别说话
- he's my neighbor. - Shh! Don't talk.
我想听听他们在说什么
I wanna hear what happens.
我不管你用什么方法...
I don't care what you do...
出了什么事吗
Something happening?
-我还以为众人皆知呢  -我就不知道
- Why, I thought everybody knew. - Well, I don't.
-汤姆在纽约有了外遇  -外遇
- Tom's got some woman in New York. - Got some woman?
她或许不懂晚饭时不该打过来
She might have the decency not to telephone at dinnertime.
你说呢
Don't you think?
你嫌我管太宽吗
Is that too much to ask?
黛西  不要无事生非
Daisy, don't create a scene.
你能上我这儿吃晚餐真好  尼克
I love seeing you at my table, Nicky.
你让我想到玫瑰  他难道不像玫瑰吗
You remind me of a rose. An absolute rose, doesn't he?
-等下吃完饭  -我可没玫瑰那么脆弱
- So after dinner, - Well, I'm not even faintly like a rose.
尼克想去镇上逛逛  对吧
Nick wanted to go into town. Right, Nick?
去耶鲁俱乐部
To the Yale Club.
尼克  就待在这儿吧
Nicky, stay.
明天我还得早起上班呢
I have to work early.
胡说
Nonsense.
-还有好多话没说  -就去喝几杯而已
- There's so much to talk about. - It's just for a drink or two.
第五次急切而刺耳的电话铃声
None of us could ignore that fifth guest's
牵动了每个人的神经
shrill metallic urgency.
-尼克  -怎么了
- Nicky. - What?
就是  我觉得一切都糟透了
It's just, well, you see, I think everything's terrible anyhow.
-是吗  -是的
- Really? - Yes.
我周游各地  看遍世间百态
I've been everywhere and seen everything and done everything.
我曾经有一段低谷时期  尼克
I've had a very bad time, Nicky.
导致我现在有点愤世嫉俗
I'm pretty cynical about everything.
你女儿一切都好吧
Your daughter, I suppose she talks and eats and everything?
你说帕米
Pammy?
是的
Oh, yes.
尼克  她出生的时候
Listen, Nick, when she was born,
天知道汤姆在哪
Tom was God knows where.
和谁鬼混在一起
with God knows whom.
我问护士
And I asked the nurse
是男孩还是女孩
if it was a boy or a girl.
她说是女孩
And she said it was a girl
我哭着说
and I wept:
真庆幸是个女孩
"I'm glad it's a girl.
我希望她做个傻姑娘
And I hope she'll be a fool.
傻姑娘才是最幸福的
That's the best thing a girl in this world can be.
美丽的傻姑娘
A beautiful little fool."
华美珍贵的事物总是很快逝去
All the bright, precious things fade so fast.
而且一去不复返
And they don't come back.
我回到家
When I arrived home
发现邻居家的码头上
I noticed that a figure
出现了一个身影
had emerged on my neighbor's dock.
直觉告诉我  他就是
And something told me it was
盖茨比先生
Mr. Gatsby.
他似乎伸着手
He seemed to be reaching toward
在黑暗中摸索着什么
something out there in the dark.
那束绿光
The green light.
我不想再说了  医生
I don't wanna talk about this, doctor.
那就写下来
Then write about it.
-写下来吗  -是的
- Write about it? - Yes.
为什么要写呢
Why would I do that?
你说过写作能给你带来慰藉
You said yourself writing brought you solace.
是的  但却不能给别人带去慰藉
Yeah, well, it didn't bring anyone else much solace.
我写得不好
I wasn't any good.
又不是给人看的
No one need ever read it.
你可以烧掉
You could always burn it.
写些什么呢
What would I write about?
什么都行
Anything.
只要能让你安心的东西都可以写
Whatever brings you ease:
一段回忆
a memory
一点想法  一个地方
a thought, a place.
写下来
Write it down.
一个地方
A place.
灰之谷是个怪异的地方
The Valley of Ashes was a grotesque place.
它是纽约的垃圾场
New York's dumping ground
在西卵区和城区之间
halfway between West Egg and the city
它的煤炭
where the burnt-out coal
点燃了纽约的纸醉金迷
that powered the booming golden city
但它已支离破碎
was discarded by men who moved dimly
在这漫天尘土中
and already crumbling
也无人愿意停留
through the powdery air.
这个古怪的农场
This fantastic farm
一直在T·J·埃克伯格医生的注视下
was ever watched by Dr. T.J. Eckleburg
他虽然被人遗忘
A forgotten oculist
却审视着这里
whose eyes brooded over it all
就像上帝之眼
like the eyes of God.
汤姆邀请我进城
Tom had invited me to town,
肯定是去参加耶鲁俱乐部的午宴
apparently for lunch at the Yale Club,
但是
but
却出现了意想不到的转折
the day took an unexpected turn.
跟我来
Come on.
-快来  -什么意思
- Come on! - What do you mean?
相信我
Trust me!
-我们这是要做什么  -你们在干什么
- What are we doing? - Where are you going?
跳
Jump!
-你要做什么  -快跳
- What are you doing? -Jump, come on!
-汤姆  -跟我来
- Tom! - Come on!
天啊
Oh, God.
汤姆  等等  等等我行吗
Tom, wait. Wait a second, would you?
跟我来  尼克
Dominate, Nick!
跟我来
Dominate!
你好  威尔逊
Hello, Wilson.
生意怎么样
How's business?
还好  没什么可抱怨的
Yeah, I can't complain.
什么时候把车卖给我
So when are you gonna sell me that car?
我正让人修着呢
Oh, I've still got my man working on it.
他修得也太慢了  不是吗
Yeah, well, he works pretty slow, don't he?
也许该卖给别人
Maybe I'd better sell it somewhere else.
别  别  别
Oh, no, no, no.
我不是那个意思  我只是...
I wasn't saying that. I was...
如果是谈生意的话  得跟我谈
If it's business, you should be talking to me.
你还不快去搬椅子来
Get some chairs why don't you,
让人家坐下
so somebody can sit down.
好的
Uh, sure.
我们谈谈生意吧
Yeah, let's talk business.
没问题
Sure.
我去搬椅子
I'll get the chairs.
桃金娘
Myrtle,
-你来招待一下  -快去
- why don't you entertain? - Hurry up.
-你好  -你好
- Hi. - Hi.
布坎南先生
Mr. Buchanan.
吃糖吗
Candy?
-不吃  谢谢  -不吃吗
- No, thank you. - No?
威尔逊夫人  这是尼克·卡罗威
Mrs. Wilson, Nick Carraway.
幸会
A pleasure.
尼克是位作家
Nick's a writer.
实际上我在搞债券
I'm in bonds actually.
我要你
I want you
搭下一列火车
get on the next train.
现在吗
Now?
是的
Yes.
我们可以养只狗吗
Can we get the dog?
-在公寓里  -听你的
- For the apartment? - Whatever you want.
布坎南先生
Hey, Mr. Buchanan!
喝汽水吗
You want a soda?
-不喝了  -不喝吗
- I'm fine. - No?
叫上你的妹妹  她会喜欢他的
Call your sister. She'll like him.
不不  不用了  谢谢
No, no, no. That's all right, thank you.
认识凯瑟琳的人都说她漂亮
Catherine's said to be very good-looking by people who know.
真的  不用了
Oh, really, I can't.
不给桃金娘面子吗
You wanna embarrass Myrtle?
那多没礼貌
That's rude.
我是凯瑟琳
I'm Catherine.
来场狂欢吗
Ain't we having a party?
我觉得
Um, I'm not sure
现在不太合适吧
now's a good time.
我正要走  实际上  有人在...
I'm just going. Actually, there are peop...
你好
Hello!
切斯特  他就是那个表哥吧
Oh, Chester, this must be the cousin.
-你真可爱  -谢谢
- Oh, you are adorable. - Oh, thank you.
我是切斯特·麦基  很高兴见到你
Chester McKee. Pleasure to meet you.
-尼克·卡罗威  -来吧
- Nick Carraway. - Come on,
-难道你不喜欢我  -撞盆栽上了
- don't you like me? - Oh. Heh. A plant.
桃金娘
Myrtle!
桃金娘小龟龟
Myrtle turtle!
我真得走了
I really must go.
快给大家拿点喝的  不然都睡着了
Get everybody a drink before they fall asleep.
汤姆  我要走了
Tom, I'm just leaving now.
尼克
Nick.
等等
Wait.
-我要走了  我得出去了  -胡闹
- I'm going. I've gotta get out of here. - Nonsense!
进去和凯瑟琳说说话
Go on in there and talk to Catherine.
我觉得不自在  黛西可是我表妹
I'm not comfortable. Daisy's my cousin.
我知道你不爱凑热闹  大学时就是这样
Listen, I know you like to watch. I remember that from college.
不  不  我不是指责你
No, no, no, I don't make any judgment.
我们有整个夏天来潇洒
We have all summer.
你是想袖手旁观呢
Now, do you wanna sit on the sideline and watch,
还是想参与进来
or do you wanna play ball?
来玩玩嘛
Play ball.
-是我们不够好吗  -来吧
- Ain't we good enough for you? - Come on!
来吧  来吧
Come on! Come on.
他是要袖手旁观
He's gonna sit on the side and watch, huh?
还是来乐呵乐呵
Or is he gonna play ball?
摘掉帽子  留下来
Take off your hat and stay a while.
对了  尼克
Oh, hey, Nick.
-麦基是搞艺术的  -摄影
- McKee is in the artistic game. - Photography.
-尼克也是搞艺术的  -不是
- Nick's artistic. - No.
-不是  不是  -真的吗
- No, no, no. - Really?
-偶尔会写作  但...  -真的吗
- I write a little, but... - Really?
你也住长岛吗
Do you live on Long Island too?
我住在西卵区
I live at West Egg.
大概一个月前  我去那参加过派对
I was there at a party about a month ago.
有个叫盖茨比的  认识吗
A man named Gatsbys. Do you know him?
我就住在他隔壁
I live right next door to him.
他是德皇威廉的表亲
He's a cousin of Kaiser Wilhelm's.
-就是那个邪恶的德国皇帝  -真的吗
- You know, the evil German king? - Really?
麦基
Hey, McKee!
把这照下来
Take a picture of that.
别这样  我才不是那种模特呢
Don't, I'm not one of those models.
如果你想拍也可以
You can if you want.
他们俩都受不了自己家的那口子
Neither of them can stand the person they're married to.
她也不喜欢威尔逊吗
Doesn't she like Wilson either?
他是个谄上媚下的人渣
He's a greasy little scumbag.
不了  谢谢  不用喝就已经飘飘然了
No, thanks, I feel just as good on nothing at all.
治疗神经的药
Nerve pills.
我在皇后区的一个医生那搞到的
I get them from a doctor in Queens.
你也来一片吗
Do you want one?
不  我的神经没问题  谢谢
Oh, no. My nerves are fine, thanks.
我一生中只醉过两次
I had been drunk just twice in my life.
第二次就是在那天下午
And the second time was that afternoon.
那晚
That night,
在汤姆为桃金娘准备的藏身公寓里
in the hidden flat that Tom kept for Myrtle
我们借着酒劲  买醉狂欢
we were buoyed by a sort of chemical madness.
我们内心深处对狂欢的渴望
A willingness of the heart
雷鸣般迸发出来
that burst thunderously upon us all.
突然间
And suddenly,
我开始喜欢上了纽约
I began to like New York.
这比耶鲁俱乐部棒多了
This is better than the Yale Club.
我们这排高踞在城市上空的
High over the city
灯火通明的窗子
our yellow windows
必定给街上观望的过客
must have contributed their share of human secrets
增添了神秘感
to the casual watcher in the street.
我曾经也像他一样
And I was him too,
仰望又寻思着
looking up and wondering.
我既置身事内
I was within
又超乎其外
and without.
我对人生的变幻莫测
Enchanted and repelled
既感陶醉  又感厌恶
by the inexhaustible variety of life.
你没权利说她的名字
You have got no right to speak her name.
黛西  黛西  黛西
Daisy, Daisy, Daisy!
你没权利说她的名字
You got no right to speak her name!
我想说就说...
I'll speak her name whenever...
天啊  你疯了
Oh, my God, you are crazy!
臭婊子
You whore!
他们会把你抓起来
They're gonna arrest you!
不知道我是怎么回的家
I have no clue how I got home
但我醒来时
but I do know that
着实有种不安的感觉
I awoke with a distinctly uneasy feeling
觉得盖茨比在盯着我
that Gatsby was watching me.
盯着你
Watching you?
是的
Yes.
盖茨比一直在盯着我
Gatsby was always watching me.
你怎么知道的
And how did you know that?
我收到一份邀请
I got an invitation.
只有我收到了邀请
I was the only one.
我是说  除我之外
By which I mean no one except me
恐怕没人真正收到过盖茨比家的邀请
ever received an actual invitation to Gatsby's.
亲爱的卡罗威先生  还望赏光我的小派对  您真诚的杰·盖茨比
其他纽约人
You see, the rest of New York
都是不请自来
simply came uninvited.
全市的人三五成群地搭车而来
The whole city packed into automobiles.
每个周末
And all weekend, every weekend
都在盖茨比家度过
ended up at Gatsby's.
不管是谁  什么工作
And I mean everyone from every walk of life
住在哪里的人都会来
from every corner of New York City,
这场缤纷夺目的嘉年华
this kaleidoscopic carnival
挤破了盖茨比家的大门
spilled through Gatsby's door.
闪开
Out of the way!
我的邀请函
My invitation.
先生  这是我的邀请函
Sir, my invitation.
这边
This Way!
大厅里满是
A caravanserai of billionaire playboy publishers
左拥右抱的出版界富豪
and their blond nurses.
沙滩上是炫耀遗产的小姐们
Heiresses comparing inheritances on Gatsby's beach.
我老板沃尔特·切斯在轮盘赌上输了钱
My boss, Walter Chase, losing money at the roulette tables.
八卦写手伺机而动
Gossip columnists alongside,
黑帮和政府官员互换号码  打成一片
gangsters and governors exchanging telephone numbers.
影星
Film stars.
百老汇导演
Broadway directors.
道德的捍卫者
Morality protectors.
叛逆的青少年
High school defectors.
这是尤因·克里普斯普林格  传言是贝多芬的后代
And Ewing Klipspringer, dubious descendent of Beethoven.
请问派对主人盖茨比先生在哪里
Do you know where I might find the host, Mr. Gatsby?
我就住隔壁
I live just next door.
盖茨比吗
Gatsby?
先生  我从未见过盖茨比先生
I've never seen Mr. Gatsby, sir.
根本没人见过他
Why, no one has.
孤身一人  又碰了一鼻子灰
Alone, and a little embarrassed.
我决定不醉不休
I decided to get roaring drunk.
我就觉得看到的是你
I thought I might see you here.
你好
Hello.
我记得你就住隔壁
I remembered you live next door.
这里就像游乐园
It's like an amusement park.
跳支舞吧
Shall we?
你收到邀请函了吗
Did you get an invitation?
来盖茨比家是不用邀请函的
People aren't invited to Gatsby's.
但是我收到了
Well, I was.
好像就我收到了
Seems I'm the only one.
盖茨比究竟是何方神圣
Who is this Gatsby?
他曾是战时德国间谍
He was a German spy during the war.
泰迪·巴顿
Teddy Barton.
尼克·卡罗威
Nick Carraway.
德国间谍吗
A German spy?
不对不对  他是德皇的杀手
No, no, no. He's the Kaiser's assassin.
-听说他杀过人  -没错
- I heard he killed a man once. - It's true.
就是杀着玩而已  也没被抓
Kills for fun, free of charge.
绝对是有通天的本领
He's certainly richer than God.
你不会真相信他杀过人吧
You don't really believe he killed a man, do you?
找到他以后  你自己问问不就知道了
Let's go find him and you can ask him yourself.
女士们先生们  掌声欢迎
Ladies and gentlemen, please welcome to the stage...
才华横溢的
the incredible
吉尔达·格蕾  因西米舞而闻名的美国艺人
吉尔达·格蕾小姐
Miss Gilda Gray!
带来查尔斯顿舞
The Charleston!
至少我还怀念着
At least I miss
环球之旅
Trips around the world
不是你的女人
Don't mean a thing
就一文不值
If I ain't your girl
宝贝  我没时间陪你耗
I ain't got time for you, baby
不管你属不属于我
Either you're mine or you're not
盖茨比先生
Mr. Gatsby?
亲爱的宝贝
Sweet baby
来吧
Come on.
此时此地
Right here, right now
但你弄错了
But you are mistaken!
因为我就是
For I am
神秘的
the mysterious
盖茨比先生
Mr. Gatsby.
你们找不到他的
You won't find him.
这房子只不过是
This house and everything in it are all part
精心布置的假象
of an elaborate disguise.
而盖茨比先生并不存在
But Mr. Gatsby doesn't exist.
呸  我碰到过他
Phooey. I've met him.
是吗  是哪一个身份的他呢
Really? Which one?
是王子
The prince?
还是间谍
The spy?
亦或是杀人犯
The murderer?
我找不出一个
I cannot find anyone
了解一点真实内幕的人
who knows anything real about Mr. Gatsby.
我不在乎
Well, I don't care.
他办了这么多大型派对
He gives large parties
很合我心意
and I like large parties.
有很多私人空间
They're so intimate.
派对小了  哪儿都能撞见人
Small parties, there isn't any privacy.
假如你说的是对的
But if that's true,
这又是为了什么
what's all this for?
我亲爱的朋友
That, my dear fellow
这是个问题
is the question.
准备好了吗
Are you ready?
小小派对  无伤大雅
A little party never killed nobody
所以就算跳到精疲力尽  依然不停息
So we gonna dance until we drop still go on
小小派对  无伤大雅
A little party never killed nobody
此时此刻就请及时行乐吧
Right here, right now is all we got
小小派对  无伤大雅
A little party never killed nobody
能请你跳这一曲吗
May I have this dance?
你个小白脸
You penniless pantywaist.
小小派对  无伤大雅
A little party never killed nobody
我把她借走了  卡罗威
I'm stealing her away. Carraway.
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen!
世界顶尖爵士舞曲过后
A jazz history of the world,
为您带来的是
and accompanying
烟花表演
fireworks!
-快点  尼克  -看看你周围
- Come on. Nick. - Look around you.
富家女是不会嫁给穷小子的
Rich girls don't marry poor boys.
她是我的
She's mine.
你看起来好眼熟
Your face is familiar.
您战时曾在第三师吗
Weren't you in the Third Division during the war?
-对  在第九营  -我在第七营
- Oh, yes, the 9th Battalion. - I was in the 7th.
-借过  -我就觉得是见过的
- Excuse me. - I knew you looked familiar.
玩得开心吗  老伙计
Having a good time, old sport?
真是太神奇了
The whole thing's incredible.
我就住隔壁呢
I live just next door.
他真给我发邀请函了  好像就我收到了
He sent me an actual invitation. Seems I'm the only one.
我还没见过盖茨比先生本人
I still haven't met Mr. Gatsby.
没人见过他
No one's met him.
听说是德皇的三表弟
They say he's third cousin to the Kaiser,
又是魔鬼的二堂弟
and second cousin to the devil.
恕我招待不周  老伙计
I'm afraid I haven't been a very good host, old sport.
我
You see,
就是盖茨比
I'm Gatsby.
您就是...
You're...
他的微笑是如此不寻常
His smile was one of those rare smiles
人这一生也难得几回见
that you may come across four or five times in life.
这微笑似乎在告诉你
It seemed to understand you,
他理解你  信任你
and believe in you just as you
恰如你内心深处的渴望
would like to be understood and believed in.
抱歉老伙计  我还以为你知道
Sorry, old sport. I thought you knew.
那个...我不知道说什么  不好意思
Please just... I don't know what to say. Please forgive me.
-没事  -我喝多了
- it's quite all right. - I've had so much to drink.
-怎么了  -盖茨比先生
- Yes? - Mr. Gatsby, sir.
-芝加哥来电  -天啊
- Chicago on the wire. - Oh,my.
我马上过去
I'll be in in just a minute.
明天上午我新买的水上滑艇试水
I'm taking my new hydroplane out in the morning.
你想一起来吗
Would you like to go with me?
什么时候
What time?
你什么时候方便
The time that suits you.
您真是太好了
Well, that's very kind of you.
很高兴再次见到你  贝克小姐
Lovely to see you again, Miss Baker.
要是有什么需要
If there's anything that you want,
尽管开口  老伙计
just ask for it, old sport.
我先失陪了
Excuse me.
过会儿再来
I will rejoin you later.
我以为他...
I expected him to be...
-是个大腹便便的糟老头吗  -对
- Old and fat? - Yes.
年轻人是不会突然冒出来
Young men don't just drift coolly out of nowhere,
在长岛买座豪宅的
and buy a palace on Long Island.
他说他以前在牛津读书
He told me once he was an Oxford man.
可我不相信
However, I don't believe it.
为什么
Why not?
不知道  就是不信
I don't know. I just don't believe he went there.
抱歉
I beg your pardon.
贝克小姐  盖茨比先生有请
Miss Baker, Mr. Gatsby would like to speak to you.
您一人前去
Alone.
叫我吗
Me?
是的  女士
Yes, madam.
尼克
Nick!
我刚才听到了最骇人的消息
I've just heard the most shocking thing.
你去哪里了  车等着呢
Where have you been? The car's waiting.
-快  得走了  -简直让人目瞪口呆
- Come on, we're leaving. - Simply amazing.
这就说得通了
It all makes sense.
解释了这一切
明白了吧
Come on.
-什么意思  -所有
- What makes sense? - Everything!
快点  别闹了
Come on, this is crazy!
-我们得走了  -但我只能说这么多
- We gotta get out of here. - Oh, but here I am tantalizing you,
因为我发了誓不能说
when I swore I wouldn't tell.
你就告诉我吧
Just tell me.
尼克  对不起  我发过誓了
Oh, Nick, I'm sorry, I swore.
发了誓不能说的
I swore I wouldn't tell.
抱歉让她走了  老伙计
Sorry to keep her from you, old sport.
别忘了明天上午的水上滑艇之约
Don't forget we're going up in that hydroplane tomorrow morning.
一定
Yes.
盖茨比先生
Mr. Gatsby, sir.
-费城来电  -知道了
- Philadelphia on the phone. - Yes.
晚安  老伙计
Night, old sport.
晚安
Good night.
谢谢你
Thank you.
怎么了
What's the matter?
没油了吗
You run out of gas?
尼克  要来看我哦
Nick! Come and see me!
下周一起喝茶
We'll have tea next week.
电话簿上找
I'm in the phone book.
我会给你打电话的
I'll call you up.
后来我们去坐了水上滑艇
Well, we rode in the hydroplane.
我又参加了两次他的派对
And I attended two more of his parties.
还借用过他家沙滩
Even made use of his beach.
但老实说  医生
But you know, doctor, I realized
我完全不了解盖茨比这个人
that I knew absolutely nothing about Gatsby at all.
直到后来...
Until...
车还不错吧  老伙计
It's pretty, isn't it, old sport?
以前是不是没见过
Haven't you ever seen it before?
专门定制的
It's all a custom job.
增压引擎
Supercharged engine.
快去穿衣服
Get dressed.
跟我去吃饭
We're going to lunch.
我说  老伙计
Look here, old sport.
你觉得我这人怎么样
What is your opinion of me, anyhow?
-我觉得吗  -对  你怎么想的
- My opinion? - Yes, yes, your opinion.
我不希望
I don't want you to get the wrong impression from all these,
你被各种奇怪的谣言误导
from all these bizarre accusations you must be hearing.
那些全是假的  你听过吧
A pack of lies, I guarantee. You've heard the stories?
-我...  -我会告诉你真相的
- Well, I... - I will tell you God's truth.
不掺一点假
God's truth about myself.
我出身于中西部的有钱人家
I am the son of very wealthy people from the Middle West.
不幸的是  家人都已去世
Sadly, all of them are dead now.
我虽在美国长大  却在牛津上学
I was brought up in America but educated at Oxford.
因为祖祖辈辈都在那里接受教育
Because all my ancestors have been educated there for years.
算是家族传统吧
You see, it's a family tradition.
他说话的方式
The way he spoke.
的确会让人怀疑他在说谎
No wonder people thought he was lying.
家人去世后  我得到了巨额遗产
After my family died, I ran into a great deal of money.
此后我就像王子一般
After that, I lived like a young prince.
游历欧洲各国
You know, in all the capitals of Europe.
-欧洲啊  -对  是欧洲
- Oh, Europe. - Yes, Europe.
巴黎  威尼斯
Paris, Venice
罗马  维也纳
Rome, Vienna
苏黎世  赫尔辛基
Zurich, Helsinki
莫斯科  伊斯坦布尔
Moscow, Istanbul
我收集珠宝
Collecting jewels,
以红宝石为主
chiefly rubies.
狩猎猛兽
Hunting big game,
画了几幅画  做些我想做的事
painting a little, things for myself only.
试图忘记忧愁...
Trying to forget something sad...
我本以为这些就够带劲的了
Just when I thought it couldn't be any more fantastical.
战争打响了  老伙计
Then came the war, old sport.
他化身战争英雄  单枪匹马拿下了德军
He became a war hero, single-handedly defeating the German army.
在阿尔贡的森林里
In the Argonne Forest,
我攻破两个机枪支队
I took two machine gun detachments so far...
当时敌众我寡  只能以一敌五
We were outnumbered 5 to 1.
那有个半英里深的峡谷
There was a half a mile gap.
德军全军覆没
There wasn't a single German soldier left standing.
我们在峡谷里呆了两天两夜
We stayed there two days and two nights.
看到横尸遍野
We saw piles of dead.
130个士兵只有16把刘易斯式机关枪
One hundred and thirty men with only 16 Lewis guns.
所有同盟国都颁发给我一枚勋章
Every Allied government gave me a medal.
连黑山共和国也不例外
Even Montenegro.
位于前南斯拉夫南部  亚德里沿岸地区
看
Here.
这个就是
That's from Montenegro.
"杰·盖茨比少校
"Major Jay Gatsby for
-骁勇善战  特授予勋章"  -没错
- valor extraordinary." - Valor extraordinary. That's right.
这个我一直随身携带
And this is something I always carry with me,
来纪念我在牛津大学的时光
a souvenir of Oxford days.
这是在三一学院照的
That was taken in Trinity quad.
左边的人现在是唐卡斯特伯爵
The man on my left is now the Earl of Doncaster.
我还有什么可说的呢
What could I say?
照片毋庸置疑是真的
The photograph was undoubtedly authentic.
但这些都是真的吗
Could it all be true?
当然  你大可不必听信我  老伙计
Of course, you don't need to take my word for it, old sport.
午宴时我会介绍个人给你认识
At lunch, I'm going to introduce you
他是纽约最有名的商人
to one of New York's most distinguished businessmen.
迈耶·沃尔夫山姆先生  我的好友
A Mr. Meyer Wolfshiem, my good friend.
此人现实中原型即是1919年黑袜丑闻的主角阿诺德·罗斯坦，美剧《大西洋帝国》中亦有该角色
他会证实我说的一切
He will confirm all I have told you
-并为我的人格做担保  -不用了
- and vouch for my good character. - I am sure that's not necessary.
不  有这个必要
Oh, but it is, though.
我觉得你应该了解下我的生活
I thought you ought to know something about my life.
我不想让你认为我是个
I didn't want you to think I was,
好吧
well,
我不想让你认为我是个无名小卒
I didn't want you to think I was some nobody.
老伙计
You see, old sport,
我今天想向你提个不情之请
I'm going to make a very big request of you today.
不情之请
A big request?
没错
Yes.
你带贝克小姐去喝茶时
Miss Baker will explain everything
她会详细解释给你
when you take her to tea.
乔丹  跟她有什么关系
Jordan? What's she got to do with it?
我保证这绝对是合法正当的
Well, I assure you it's nothing underhand.
贝克小姐是个诚实的运动员
Miss Baker's an honest sportswoman.
她不会做错事的
She wouldn't do anything that wasn't all right.
靠边停车
Pull over!
-靠边停车  -好的  老伙计  好的
- Pull over to the curb! - All right, old sport. All right.
杰·盖茨比
果然是
Right you are!
下次不会麻烦您了  盖茨比先生
I'll know you next time, Mr. Gatsby!
-抱歉了  -谢谢你
- Excuse me. - Thank you.
你以前牛津的同学吗
One of your old Oxford pals?
我以前帮过警察局长一次
Well, I was able to do the commissioner a favor once.
他每年都给我寄圣诞贺卡
He sends me a Christmas card every year.
他应该也去那吃午饭
I imagine he'll be at lunch too. Heh.
车开上桥后  我变得无比困惑
By the time we reached the bridge, I was impossibly confused.
我不知道该想些什么
I didn't know what to think.
但从皇后大桥上放眼望去
But the city seen from the Queensboro Bridge,
这个城市还是只如初见
is always the city seen for the first time
让你觉得世间所有美景
in its first wild promise of all the mystery
还有秘密
and the beauty
都在这里
in the world.
我想
Anything can happen
既然过了桥  就一切皆有可能了
now that we've slid over this bridge, I thought.
一切
Anything at all.
盖茨比都已经是我朋友了
Even Gatsby could happen.
可以  不错
Yes, absolutely.
小子
My boy!
迈耶  迈耶  迈耶
Meyer, Meyer, Meyer.
你身上味道不错
Mm. Smell so good.
-你看着挺不错的  -你不也是
- Look at you! - Look at you.
卡罗威先生
Mr. Carraway,
这位是迈耶·沃尔夫山姆  我的好友
this is my good friend, Mr. Meyer Wolfshiem.
很高兴认识你  卡罗威先生
A wonderful pleasure, Mr. Carraway.
我也是
My pleasure.
你的事我可都知道
I know all about you.
-这样啊  -没错  盖茨比先生
- I see. - Yes! Mr. Gatsby's
-总是提起您  -是吗
- always talking about you. - Really?
我们走吧
Shall we?
来吧
Come.
我们来共享小型"午宴"
Join us for a little "Lunch".
-放开我  -出去  滚出去
- Hands off! - Out! Out you go!
放开我
Get off me!
告诉沃尔特·切斯  别乱说话
Tell Walter Chase he keeps his mouth shut
否则别想拿钱
or he doesn't get a penny.
我们等下再谈这事
We'll talk about that later.
还是冰威士忌吗  盖茨比先生
Highballs, Mr. Gatsby?
是的
Highballs it is.
-明白  -照顾一下我朋友
- All right. - You take care of my friend.
看看谁来了
Look who's here.
看到他的拳头了吗
You see these fists?
他可是下届重量级拳击冠军
He's the next heavyweight champion.
代我向你老板问好
Pay my respects to your boss.
你好  杰
Hey, Jay!
你被捕啦
You're under arrest! Ha-ha-ha!
你要当心啦
You be careful, now.
你就快变成爵士舞神了  局长
You're turning into a real jazz hound, commissioner.
-那位是警察局长  -盖茨比先生
- That's the commissioner. - Mr. Gatsby,
您的桌子备好了
your table is ready.
-盖茨比  -见到你很高兴
- Gatsby! - Good to see you.
真是不错啊
Yeah, that's fantastic.
你要当心这些桌上的客人啊  议员
You be careful at those tables now, senator.
我会在你身上下注的  杰
I'll put a bet on for you, Jay!
我点的龙虾
We'll have the lobster.
搭配松露和上好的香草
It's decorated with truffles and fine herbs.
您的债券生意怎么样了  卡罗威先生
So, how is the bond business, Mr. Carraway?
很好  谢谢
Fine. Thank you.
我知道您在寻找商业伙伴
I understand you're looking for a business connection.
不  不  不对
No. No, no, no.
不对  不对
No, no, no.
他不是那个人  迈耶
This isn't the man, Meyer.
他是我说的那个朋友
This is the friend that I told you about.
抱歉抱歉
Oh, I beg your pardon.
我记错人了
I had a wrong man.
不好意思  我要去打个电话
If you'll excuse me, I have to make that call.
运气不错吧  议员
Any luck, senator?
真是个绅士
What a gentleman.
出生于中西部最富庶的家族
From one of the finest families in the Midwest.
可惜  家里人都去世了
Sadly, all dead now.
战后  我初次得见盖茨比先生
When I first made the pleasure of Mr. Gatsby's acquaintance
我就知道
just after the war,
他很有教养
I knew I'd discovered a man of fine breeding.
他是战争英雄
A war hero.
勋章无数
Such medals.
而且
And,
and
还是牛津大学的高材生
an Oxford man.
你知道牛津大学吗
You know Oxford?
知道  我听说过
Yes, I've heard of it.
那你就知道见到他这样的男人
Then you'd know that when it comes to married women,
是绝对没人担心妻子出轨的
a man like this can be trusted.
和像您这样的朋友待在一起时
With a friend with someone like you,
他都不会多看你妻子一眼
he'd never so much as look at your wife.
我还没结婚
I'm not married.
但你在华尔街上班  是吧
But you work on Wall Street, right?
没错
Yes.
在看我的领带夹是吗
Looking at my tiepin?
一颗上好的人类臼齿
Finest specimen of human molar.
先生们
Gentlemen.
一切无恙吧
Everything all right?
是的  没事  我们
Yes! Yes. We,
我们在讨论人妻
we were just talking about other people's wives.
别人的妻子吗
Other people's wives?
-没错  -是吗
- Yes. - Really?
我谈完了  所以我就留二位
Well, my work here is done. I'm going to leave you gentlemen
继续讨论运动和女人吧
to talk about your sports and your women.
别人的妻子
Other people's wives.
女士们  你们好
Hello, ladies.
他究竟是什么人
Who is he, anyhow?
演员吗
An actor?
迈耶吗
Meyer?
不  他是个赌徒
No, no. He's a gambler.
是他平息了1919年的"黑袜丑闻"
He's the man who fixed the 1919 World Series.
以芝加哥白袜队和世界职业棒球赛为中心的赌赛丑闻
他解决的吗
Fixed it?
是的
Fixed it.
他是怎么做到的
Well, how'd he manage that?
大概是瞅准了时机吧
Saw the opportunity, I suppose.
他是个精明的人
He's a very smart man.
老伙计  我想谈下有关贝克小姐
Now, old sport, about Miss Baker
和我的那个请求的事
and that request we spoke of.
尼克  尼克
Nick? Nick!
汤姆  见到你真高兴
Tom! Funny seeing you!
-你过得不错吧  -是的
- How have you been? - Yeah.
-好  -尼克  你还没打电话给黛西
- Good. - Nick, Daisy is furious
她气得要命
that you haven't called.
盖茨比先生  这位是布坎南先生
Mr. Gatsby, this is Mr. Buchanan.
很高兴认识你
It's a pleasure to make your acquaintance.
没想到在这能碰见你
Never would have expected to find you in this temple of virtue.
我来和盖茨比先生共进午餐
I was having lunch with Mr. Gatsby.
需要帮助吗  先生
Can I help you, sir?
我在找乔丹·贝克
Jordan Baker
那个运动明星  高尔夫球手  没事了
the famous sporting star? The golfer? I see.
我看到她了  谢谢
I've spotted her. Thank you.
终于找到你了
There you are.
你和盖茨比在耍什么把戏
What game are you and Gatsby Playing at?
-这位先生是客人吗  -请等一下
- The gentleman will be joining? - Excuse me. One moment.
-尼克  拜托  -简直匪夷所思
- Nick, please. - It's all rather strange.
他开豪车来接我
He picks me up in his fancy car.
-开始向我讲述他的人生  -小声点
- Going on about his life. - Keep your voice down.
别人会听见的
People can hear you.
这到底是什么请求
What is this enormous request?
他想让你邀请黛西共进茶会
He wants you to invite Daisy to tea.
黛西
Daisy?
和盖茨比
And Gatsby.
为什么
Why?
我不知从何讲起
I don't quite know where to start.
我碰到盖茨比先生的那晚
You see, I didn't realize
我才知道一切
until the other night that I'd met Gatsby.
五年前  在路易斯维尔[美国城市]
Five years ago. In Louisville.
那天  我买了新的英式高尔夫鞋
It was the day I got my new English golf shoes.
当时泰勒军营的那些军官们
Daisy was by far the most popular girl with
都对黛西情有独钟
the officers from Camp Taylor.
你好  乔丹
Hello, Jordan.
其中一位军官和她同坐在车里
One of them was in the car with her.
他就是盖茨比
It was Gatsby.
他那深情款款的双眼
The way he looked at her is the way
是所有姑娘梦寐以求的
all girls want to be looked at.
给我讲讲这件事吧
So, tell me what happened.
我也不知道
Well, I don't know.
冲啊
Charge!
盖茨比被派去了战场
Gatsby was sent off to war.
战争结束后
When the war ended
黛西还在等
Daisy waited.
但不知为何  盖茨比没回来
But for some unknown reason, Gatsby couldn't return.
钻石王老五  铁路之王得路易斯维尔美人芳心
一年后
A year later,
芝加哥的汤姆·布坎南横刀夺爱
Tom Buchanan of Chicago swept in and stole her away.
给了她一串价值三十五万美元的珍珠
He gave her a string of pearls worth $350,000.
但婚礼当天上午
But the morning of the wedding
黛西收到了一封信
Daisy received a letter.
告诉他们黛西改主意了
Tell them Daisy's changed her mind!
-这是怎么回事  -黛西  别这样
- What is this? - Daisy, please!
-给我  -不
- Hand it to me! - No!
离我远点
Leave me alone!
乔丹  这事谁都不能知道
Jordan, no one must know about this.
-信里说了什么  -我不知道
- What was in the letter? - I don't know.
她不肯告诉我
She wouldn't tell me.
但一切都太晚了
But it was too late.
那天下午五点  黛西·费
That day at 5:00, Daisy Fay
与汤姆·布坎南完婚
married Tom Buchanan
婚礼排场在路易斯维尔空前绝后
with more pomp and circumstance than Louisville had ever seen.
年度婚礼  路易斯维尔社交新秀说"我愿意"
祝贺你  布坎南先生
Congratulations, Mr. Buchanan!
跟着箭头  赶上潮流  箭牌领男装
蜜月后  我在圣巴巴拉见过他们
After the honeymoon, I saw them in Santa Barbara.
相当感人  真的
Well, it was touching, really.
我从没见过感情这么深的夫妻
I'd never seen a girl so in love with her husband.
一周以后  汤姆出了车祸
A week later, Tom crashed his car.
车上还有个圣巴巴拉酒店女服务员
The girl with him was a chambermaid at the Santa Barbara Hotel.
所有的报纸都报道了
It got into all the papers.
-真是太巧了  -什么太巧了
- It's a strange coincidence. - What is?
盖茨比的房子和他们家就一水之隔
The fact that Gatsby's house is just across the bay.
这绝非巧合
It's no coincidence.
他买下那房子  就是为了接近她
He bought that house to be near her.
他办那些派对  就是希望她能来一次
He threw all those parties hoping she'd wander in one night.
他常常问起黛西
He constantly asked about Daisy.
只不过我先知道的这段历史
I was just the first person that knew her.
为一个五年没见的姑娘做了这一切
All that for a girl he hasn't seen in five years.
现在却只要我请她来喝茶
And now he just wants me to invite her over to tea.
厚积薄发
The modesty of it.
真是难以置信  是吧
Kind of takes your breath away, doesn't it?
晚上好  亲爱的
Evening, sweethearts.
去哪儿呢  孩子们
Where are you kids going?
-长岛吧  -你说我要不要...
- Long Island, please. - And you think I should...
我是说  黛西会想见盖茨比吗
I mean, does Daisy want to see Gatsby?
绝对不能让她知道
She's absolutely not to know.
你把她请过来就好
You're supposed to invite her over
他就可以假装路过
so he can happen to pass by.
我记得我内心很纠结
I remember feeling torn.
把我已婚的表妹黛西和我不熟悉的男人
Was it right to bring my cousin Daisy, a married woman
撮合在一起  合适吗
together with a man I hardly knew?
我回到家时  盖茨比家灯火通明
When I returned home, Gatsby's was lit from tower to cellar
好像又一场狂欢
as if for another wild party.
但却没有一丝声响
But there wasn't a sound.
-谢谢你  -晚上愉快
- Thank you. - Have a good night.
你家就像世界博览会  或者科尼岛
Your place looks like the World's Fair or Coney Island.
科尼岛  纽约布鲁克林南部娱乐中心
-是吗  -是的
- Does it? - Yes.
我只是随便看看这些屋子
Well, I've just been glancing into some of the rooms.
你说我们去科尼岛怎么样  老伙计
What do you say we go to Coney Island, old sport?
可以坐我的车去
We could take my car.
今天太晚了
Oh, uh, it's too late tonight.
那我们可以跳进泳池凉快凉快
We could take a plunge in the swimming pool.
我整个夏天都还没用过它
I haven't made use of it all summer.
我得去睡觉了
I must go to bed.
那好
All right.
我很乐意
Happy to do it.
我会给黛西打电话
I'm going to call Daisy and
-请她来喝茶的  -太好了
- invite her to tea. - That's all right.
-你觉得哪天方便  -你觉得哪天方便
- What day would suit you? - What day would suit you?
我可不想给你添麻烦
I don't want to put you to any trouble.
后天怎么样
Day after tomorrow all right?
后天吗
Day after tomorrow?
我  我想
Well, I, I'd,
我得找人修一下草坪
See, I'd want to get the grass cut.
听我说  老伙计
Well, look here, old sport.
你赚的钱不多吧  对吗
You don't make much money, do you?
-不太多  -恕我冒昧
- Not really. - If you'll forgive me.
我正好在做一点小生意
You see, I happen to run a little business on the side.
相当于副业
A sort of sideline.
你知道我在说什么  对吧
You understand what I'm saying, right?
你是卖债券的  是吧  老伙计
You do sell bonds, don't you, old sport?
-我正在努力卖  -好的
- I'm trying to. - Right.
干这个  可是要相当的保密
Well, happens to be a rather confidential sort of thing
不过钱倒是不少
but you might make a nice bit of money on the side.
不用了  谢谢你  我太忙了
No, thank you. I have my hands full.
你不用和沃尔夫山姆有任何来往
You wouldn't have to do any business with Wolfshiem,
我保证
I assure you.
举手之劳  杰  举手之劳而已
It's a favor, Jay. Just a favor.
真的  我很乐意帮忙
Yes. Happy to do it.
-举手之劳  -是的
- Favor? - Yes.
那好  晚安
Well, good night.
晚安
Good night.
早上好
Good morning.
有份报纸说  雨大概四点会停
One of the papers says they thought the rain would stop about 4.
我想那是...我想那是《新闻报》
I think it was the... I think it was the Journal.
进门右拐  先生们
Just in to the right, gentlemen.
右拐  放在客厅里  谢谢大家
To the right in the living room. Thank you.
一切还好吗
Is everything all right?
草看起来很好  如果你问的是这个
The grass looks fine, if that's what you mean.
草
Grass?
什么草
What grass?
我买了蛋糕
I bought cakes.
你有...
Have you...
你需要的东西都有了吗
Have you got everything you need?
可能花多了点
Perhaps more flowers.
我觉得他们干得很不错  你说呢
I think they did a fine job, don't you?
很漂亮
Beautiful.
是不是太多了
You think it's too much?
这正是你想要的
Uh, I think it's what you want.
我也这么觉得
I think so too.
我不能一直等着
I can't wait all day.
我要走了
I'm leaving.
别傻了  再过两分钟就四点了
Don't be silly. It's two minutes to 4.
没有人会来喝茶的  这太...
No one's coming to tea! It's too...
是她来了
It's her!
这真是你住的地方吗  亲爱的
Is this absolutely where you live, my dearest one?
是的  这很合我胃口
Yes, it suits me.
为什么让我一个人来
Why did I have to come alone?
你爱上我了吗
Are you in love with me?
这是卡罗威城堡的秘密
Oh, it's the secret of Carraway Castle.
让你的司机去兜个大圈
Tell your chauffeur to go far away.
一小时后再回来  费尔迪
Come back in an hour Ferdie.
他叫费尔迪
His name is Ferdie.
我的天啊
Oh. My goodness.
真不敢相信
I can't believe it.
你...你抢劫花房了吗
You... did you ransack a greenhouse?
这家伙真是爱上我了
He is in love with me.
劳驾
Would you?
真有趣
That's funny.
什么真有趣
What's funny?
你这是干什么
What are you doing?
我非常高兴能再次见你
I'm certainly glad to see you again.
你好  我
Hi. I'm,
我也非常高兴能见到你
I'm certainly glad to see you, as well.
我们...我们...
We've... We've...
我们见过面
We've met before.
我马上找人来修
I'll have someone come repair this immediately.
抱歉弄坏了你的钟
Sorry about the clock.
-那钟很老了  -但很漂亮
- That's an old clock. - Lovely, though.
-漂亮的钟  -是啊
- A lovely clock. - Yes.
我们好几年没见了
We haven't met for many years.
到十一月  就满五年了
Five years next November.
喝茶吗
Tea?
-谢谢  老伙计  -谢谢  亲爱的
- Yes, thank you, old sport. - Darling, thank you.
-柠檬还是糖  -都不用
- Lemon or sugar? - Neither.
都不加  谢谢你
Plain. Thank you.
我得去一趟城里
I just have to pop into town
-城里  -马上就回来
- Town? - I'll be right back.
尼克  我有话要和你说
Nick, I've gotta speak to you about something.
-好的  我马上回来  -老天
- Yes. I'll be right back. - God.
这是个错误  这是个巨大的错误
This was a mistake. This was a terrible, terrible mistake.
你只是有些紧张了  黛西也是
You're just embarrassed. Daisy's embarrassed too.
-她也紧张吗  -是的
- She's embarrassed? - Yes.
就和你一样
Just as much as you are.
别这么大声
Don't talk so loud.
你别这么不成熟  太失礼了
You're acting like a little boy. You're being rude.
黛西一个人在里面  而你...
Daisy's in there all alone and you're...
看看我写下的部分
Looking over my story so far
我想起  那是我在那年夏天  第二次
I'm reminded that for the second time that summer
为别人保守秘密了
I was guarding other people's secrets.
再一次地  我既置身事内
Once again, I was within
又超乎其外
and without.
雨停了
It's stopped raining.
是啊
Yes.
雨真的停了
It has, hasn't it?
你觉得那怎么样  黛西
What do you think of that, Daisy?
过来看看
Come look.
尼克  真有意思
Oh, Nicky. How funny.
瞧啊  那是我家
Look, it's my house.
就在对岸
Just there across the bay.
我知道
I know.
从我家也能看到这番景致
I have the same view from my place.
你家在哪
Where's your place?
尼克  我想请你和黛西都到我家来
Nick, I want you and Daisy both to come over to my house.
我想带她转转
I'd like to show her around.
你确定要我一起来吗
You sure you want me to come?
当然了  老伙计
Absolutely, old sport.
当然了
Absolutely.
拉德纳  把大门打开
Ladner, open the gates.
把大门打开
Open the gates!
这大门是诺曼底一座城堡里的
I had the gates brought in from a castle in Normandy.
-杰  真宏伟  -喜欢吗
- Oh, Jay. It's so grand. - You like it?
太喜欢了
I love it.
但你一个人怎么住呢
But how do you live here all alone?
我并不是一个人
Well, I don't.
这总是有有趣的、有名的人
I keep it always full of interesting, celebrated people.
跟我来
Come with me.
这房子很不错吧
The house looks well, doesn't it?
看到阳光下城堡正面的效果了吗
See the way the whole front catches the light like that?
多壮观
Oh, it's splendid.
快点  你们俩  我要好好逛一逛
Come on, you two. I want the royal tour.
金雕牌
你们要知道  我喜欢跟上时代的潮流
You must understand that I like all things that are modern.
挤一挤这橙子  汁就出来了  很简单
Presses the orange it all comes out there. Simple.
谁想来一局高尔夫
Anyone for a round of golf?
你知道我是冠军高尔夫球手吧
You do know I'm a champion golfer, don't you?
-好极了  -那来啊
- Great! - Well, go on.
我觉得我们可以...
I thought we could...
这相机真棒  最新款
Remarkable little camera. Latest design.
我来教你  我来教你怎么做
Let me show you. I'll show you how it's done.
-尼克  接着拍  -好
- Nick, keep filming. - All right.
-她会挥一下  -我准备好了
- She's gonna take a swing. - I'm ready.
瞄准  击球
Aim. Fore!
我真野蛮
I'm such a brute.
来张特写吗
You ready for your close-up?
-我要把每一刻都记下来  -你好夺目
- I don't want to forget a single moment. - You're shimmering.
她这样子可以上《时尚》杂志封面了
She looks like she could be on the cover of Vogue.
把相机打开
Turn on the camera!
-你去哪儿了  -慢点
- Where did you go? - Slow down.
慢点
Slow down.
太漂亮了
It's beautiful.
是沃立舍  定制的
It's a custom Wurlitzer.
有人会弹吗
Can anyone play that?
沃立舍  美国钢琴品牌
克里普斯普林格会弹  去把尤因叫醒
Klipspringer can. Someone wake Ewing.
-好的  先生  -音乐
- Of course, sir. - Music!
这样我们就可以彻夜狂舞了
And then we can dance all night.
尤因是个天才  什么曲子都会
Ewing's a genius, plays anything.
那我要一首查尔斯顿舞曲
Then I demand a Charleston.
她让一切都熠熠生辉  不是吗  老伙计
She makes it look so splendid, don't you think, old sport?
有人在英国帮我买衣服
I have a man in England who buys me clothes.
从没见过这样的东西
I've never seen anything like it.
给姑娘的东西
Something for the lady.
每到换季时  他都把当季的服饰送来
He sends over a selection at the beginning of each season.
这些是丝的
These are silk.
-杰  -这些是法兰绒的
- Jay! - These are flannel.
真是太漂亮了
They're so beautiful!
印度棉的
Indian cotton.
停下吧  杰
Stop it. Jay!
亚麻的
Linen.
-尼克  他疯了  -我可帮不了你
- Nicky he's a madman! - I can't help you!
法兰绒
Flannel!
你要把每一件都重新叠好了
You're going to have to refold every single one of them.
你会把衣服弄坏的
You'll ruin them!
杰  快停下
Jay! Stop it.
-接着  -别
- Right here! - No!
杰
Jay!
怎么了
What is it?
黛西  黛西  亲爱的  怎么了
Daisy, Daisy, darling, what is it?
这让我很难过
It makes me sad.
为什么
Why?
因为...
Because...
那迷失的五年  在黛西唇边徘徊
Five lost years struggled on Daisy's lips.
她却只说出
But all she could manage was:
为什么
Why?
因为我从没见过这么漂亮的衣服
Because I've never seen such beautiful shirts before.
要不是有雾
If it wasn't for the mist
我们就能看见绿光了
we could see the green light.
什么绿光
What green light?
你家码头彻夜闪烁的绿光
The one that burns all night at the end of your dock.
或许  盖茨比意识到了
Possibly it had occurred to Gatsby that
那道绿光的象征意义
the colossal significance of that light
已经不复存在了
had vanished forever.
现在它不过是码头上的一道绿光而已
Now it was once again just a green light on a dock.
他为之着魔的东西少了一样
And his count of enchanted objects had diminished by one.
这是谁
Who's this?
-你父亲吗  -不是
- Your father? - Oh, no.
那是丹·科迪先生  老伙计
That's Mr. Dan Cody, old sport.
他已经去世了
He's dead now.
很多年前  他是我最好的朋友
He used to be my best friend many years ago.
你从没告诉我你剪过庞帕多发型
You never told me you had a pompadour.
还有过一艘游艇
Or a yacht.
我要给你看个东西
I wanna show you something.
坐吧
Have a seat.
这些是我收集的剪报
These are a lot of clippings I collected.
关于你的
About you.
你还留着我的信
You saved my letters.
这是我弄到的第一张你的照片
This was my first photo of you.
你还记得这封信吗
You remember this letter here?
我们不能失去彼此
We can't lose each other
不能让这华丽的爱落得一场空
and let all this glorious love end in nothing.
快回家吧
Come home.
黛西·费订婚
我就在这里等待  期待
I'll be here waiting and hoping
每一个有你在的美梦都成真
for every long dream of you to come true.
失陪一下
Excuse me.
先生  斯莱格尔在底特律来电
Sir, Slagle's in Detroit.
我现在不方便说话  老伙计
I can't talk now, old sport.
他必须知道小镇是什么样
He must know what a small town is.
不  你给我听着  给我听着
No, you listen to me. Listen to me.
我说了  是个小镇
I said a small town.
他得知道小镇是什么样
He must know what a small town is.
听我说  他要是以为底特律是个小镇
Listen to me, he's of no use to us if Detroit is his idea
就对我们没用处了  你明白吗
of a small town, you understand?
我们换个时间聊  老伙计
We'll chat later, old sport.
好的
All right.
克里普斯普林格
Klipspringer.
他一定是醒了
He must be awake.
来吧
Shall we?
真希望能和你一起经历所有美好
I wish I'd done everything on earth with you.
就这样一辈子
All my life.
真希望一直这样
I wish it could always be like this.
会的
It will be.
真希望抱着黛西  就让盖茨比满足了
If only it had been enough for Gatsby just to hold Daisy.
但他对他和黛西的人生有个宏大的计划
But he had a grand vision for his life and Daisy's part in it.
直到那个夏末
It wasn't until the end of that summer
我最后一次见到盖茨比
on the last night I saw Gatsby
他才告诉我
that he told me of
他小时候对未来生活的憧憬
the life he had dreamed for himself since he was a boy.
你知道吗  医生
You see, doctor
盖茨比的真名是
Gatsby's real name was
詹姆斯·盖茨
James Gatz.
他的父母是北达科他州身无分文的农民
His parents were dirt-poor farmers from North Dakota.
但他从不认他们为自己的父母
But he never accepted them as his parents at all.
在自己的想象中  他是上帝之子
In his own imagination, he was a son of God,
注定成就伟业
destined for future glory.
为追随命运
Chasing this destiny,
十六岁的盖茨远走他乡
a 16-year-old Gatz ran far, far away.
一天下午  在苏必利尔湖的岸边
One afternoon, off the coast of Lake Superior,
他看见一艘游艇处于险境
he spotted a yacht in peril.
他奋力划行  拯救了那游艇和它的主人
He rowed out and rescued the vessel and its captain,
酒鬼富豪  丹·科迪
alcoholic millionaire Dan Cody.
船在哪儿
Where's the boat?
你要撞上浅滩了
You're gonna hit the shoal!
先生  我们要撞上浅滩了
Come on, sir! We're gonna hit the shoal!
你他妈的在干嘛
What the hell are you doing,
老伙计
old sport?
这就是他的机会  他抓住了
This was his opportunity and he seized it.
就在那时  我决定改名叫杰·盖茨比
And I decided right then and there to call myself Jay Gatsby.
他开着游艇驶离了危险  也驶向了未来
He sailed the yacht out of danger and into his future.
富豪看到了他的技巧和雄心
Gatsby showed skill and ambition.
五年里  他们航遍了世界
And for five years, they sailed the world.
他很不错  老丹
He was all right, old Dan.
他什么都教我
He taught me everything.
如何像绅士一般打扮  谈吐  做事
How to dress, act and speak like a gentleman.
盖茨比  杰·盖茨比
Gatsby. Jay Gatsby.
这船状况很好  不是吗
She looks well, doesn't she,
盖茨比希望能继承科迪的财产
Gatsby hoped to inherit Cody's fortune.
-老伙计  -但科迪死后
- old sport? - But when Cody died,
科迪的家人骗去本该由盖茨比继承的部分
Gatsby was cheated of his inheritance by Cody's family.
他表面上还能继续扮绅士
He'd been left with the ability to play the gentleman,
但实际上  他又一次身无分文了
but he was once again dirt-poor.
盖茨比的惊人财富  钱  钱  钱  还是钱
盖茨比先生要买下我们的城市吗  投资垄断引来更多关注
杰来兑现了  盖茨比冲击了华尔街财富
盖茨比投资摩天大楼  "投资我们的未来"
杰什么钱都出得起  派对  晚宴  公园  学校  图书馆  华尔街之王算什么  来见见杰·盖茨比玩转证券市场  屡战屡胜
钱究竟从何而来  盖茨比  神秘百万财富引漫天传言
到了盛夏
By midsummer,
盖茨比成了头版新闻
Gatsby was front page news.
他的钱从何而来
Where did the money come from?
这是整个纽约都想知道的
That's what all of New York wanted to know.
汤姆陪黛西参加盖茨比的一个豪华派对时
And it was the same question on Tom's mind
脑子里也在想着这个问题
when he accompanied daisy to one of Gatsby's glittering parties.
我马上回来
I'll be right back.
这些暴发户  基本上都是
You know, a lot of these newly rich people are just
-倒卖私酒的  -盖茨比不是
- filthy bootleggers. - Not Gatsby.
他是个商人  他开了很多杂货店
He's a businessman. He owned a lot of drugstores.
商人
Businessman!
请让我介绍一下顾里克议员
May I introduce Senator Gulick?
-这是卡罗威先生  -议员
- This is Mr. Carraway. - Senator.
-布坎南太太  -倾国倾城
- Mrs. Buchanan. - Charmed.
受宠若惊
Delighted.
还有  布坎南先生
Oh, and Mr. Buchanan
马球运动员
the polo player.
不  我不是
No, not me.
见到布坎南家的人总是令人快乐
Always a pleasure to meet a Buchanan.
-见到您也是  -议员  我一会儿再去找你
- Likewise. - Senator, I'll catch up with you later.
赌桌边上见
Perhaps at the craps table.
我可不想被说成马球运动员
I'd rather not be the polo player.
汤姆  你该为自己的成就感到骄傲
Tom. You should be proud of your achievements.
我带你们转转吧
May I show you around?
好啊
Sure.
那些名人长什么样
You must know the faces
-你应该都知道吧  -当然
- of many people you've heard of! - Absolutely.
我们不经常出去
We don't go around very much.
-我可能一个人也不认得  -是吗
- I don't think I recognize a single person. - Is that so?
你可能知道那边那位小姐
Perhaps you know that lady right there.
那是马琳·穆恩  我喜欢她的电影
It's Marlene Moon. I adore her pictures.
要不要我介绍你们认识一下
Would you like me to introduce you?
我真的不想被说成是马球运动员
I'd really rather not be the polo player.
这些东西真是令人激动
These things excite me so.
漂亮的舞姿
Nice little dance.
我想我们见过面  布坎南先生
I believe we've met before, Mr. Buchanan.
大概一个月前
About a month ago.
对了
That's right.
你当时和尼克一起
And you were with Nick here.
-在理发店  -不用  谢谢
- At the barbershop. - No, thank you.
没错
That's right.
我认识你的妻子
See, I know your wife.
是吗
That so?
是的
Yes.
盖茨比先生
Mr. Gatsby, sir.
-斯莱格尔先生来了  -现在不行
- Mr. Slagle is here. - Not now. Not now.
吉他演奏
And Guitars with:
狐步舞曲
"The Foxtrot."
布坎南先生
Mr. Buchanan.
希望您不介意
Would you mind terribly?
当然不介意
Of course not.
我想我可以自娱自乐
I think I can keep myself amused.
给您记下别人家地址
In case you need to take down any addresses.
请让一让  劳驾
Please move aside. Excuse me.
又一个绝妙的派对  杰
Another swell party, Jay.
小心蛇蝎美人  麦克勒南先生
Be careful for the snake charmer, Mr. McLennehan.
这都是按你自己的想象建造的吗
Is all this made entirely from your own imagination?
不
No.
你一直都在其中
You see, you were there all along,
我的每一个念头
in every idea,
每一个抉择
in every decision.
当然  如果有什么不合你的意
Of course, if anything is not to your liking
我就把它改了
I'll change it.
很完美
It's perfect.
出自你完美的  不可抗拒的想象力
From your perfect irresistible imagination.
我想知道他到底在哪儿认识黛西的
I wonder where the devil he met Daisy.
-我一会儿来找你  -好的
- I'll find you. - All right.
跟我来
Come with me.
借过  劳驾
Coming through, please.
不好意思
Pardon me.
谢谢
Thank you.
有一个男人  有一个男人
There's a man. There's a man.
看见我老婆了吗
Have you seen my wife?
没有
No.
有一会儿没见她了
Not for a while.
威士忌
Whiskey.
真奇怪  议员刚刚看到她在这里
It's funny, the senator just saw her down here.
真希望我们可以远走高飞
I wish we could just run away.
远走高飞
Run away?
不
No.
黛西  亲爱的  那样
Daisy, darling, that,
那样不光彩
that wouldn't be respectable.
你住在这附近吗  尼克
You live around here, Nick?
就在隔壁
Just next door.
是吗
Is that so?
我们就住在这里
We're gonna live here
在这个房子里
in this house.
就你和我
You and me.
亲爱的
Darling
是时候告诉汤姆了
it's time to tell Tom.
别这样  伙计们
Come on, boys.
让开
Scram!
晚安  先生们
Good night, gentlemen.
好一场马戏表演
What a circus.
好吧
Well
如果你看到她
if you see her
告诉她
I'll be looking for her.
我在找她
You tell her.
还记得我们一起的快乐时光吗
Remember how much fun we had?
再来一次有什么不好的呢
I don't know why we can't just have fun like that again.
有人吗
Hello?
嗨  尼克
Hello, Nicky.
我们在吵架
We're having a row.
-吵什么  -吵
- What about? - About...
架
...things.
关于未来
About the future.
这个纸醉金迷
The future of...
帝国的未来
...the colored empires.
汤姆
It's Tom.
-正在满派对找  -先生
- He's wandering around the party looking-- - Sir.
盖茨比先生
Mr. Gatsby, sir.
斯莱格尔先生情绪很激动
It's Mr. Slagle. He's quite emotional.
失陪
Excuse me.
尼克  陪陪黛西
Nick. Would you mind terribly?
当然
Of course.
盖茨比离开
Gatsby disappeared
去处理一些争执
to deal with a dispute of some sort.
黛西一直等着
Daisy waited
但是盖茨比没能回来
but Gatsby was unable to return.
这里的人都爱冲动  我只相信你
With these hot-headed types in here, I rely on you.
但你没空  所以才闹出那事
But you were not available. A scene was made.
你到底怎么了  杰
What's going on with you, Jay?
你去哪了
Where were you?
和尼克在一起  盖茨比先生带我们转转
With Nicky. Mr. Gatsby was showing us the grounds.
他肯定费了好大劲儿
He certainly must have...
搞这动物园样的聚会
...strained himself to get this menagerie together.
我想知道他是谁  他想干什么
I'd like to know who he is and what he does.
不要问我为什么  肯定能找到理由
And I think I'll make a point of finding out.
忠贞不渝[拉丁文]
-我不确定  问厨房里的人  -靠左
- I'm not sure. Ask them in the kitchen. - To the left.
对
Yeah
把这些堆车库里  送进城
we'll pile that stuff in the garage, it's going back to town.
哈
Well
你在这  黛西刚走
there you are. Daisy just left.
她让我告诉你
She asked me to tell you
她过得很愉快
she had a wonderful time.
她不喜欢
She didn't like it.
她当然喜欢
Of course she did.
不不不
No, no, no.
她不喜欢  她玩得不开心
No, she didn't like it. She did not have a good time.
我现在觉得
I feel so far
离她很远
away from her now.
很难使她理解
It's so hard to make her understand.
你是说舞会吗
You mean about the party?
舞会
The party?
我根本不关心什么舞会
I couldn't care less about the parties.
舞会结束了  先生们
That'll be all for now, gentlemen.
-谢谢  -谢谢  先生
- Thank you. - Thank you, sir.
你瞧
You see
她得去告诉汤姆她没爱过他
she has to tell Tom that she never loved him.
什么
What?
是的
Yes.
然后我们就回路易斯维尔  她父母家
Then we can go back to Louisville to her parents' house.
她父母很友善  老伙计
Her parents are lovely people, old sport. We'll be
我们就在那结婚
married there.
你看
See...
我和黛西会重新开始
See, Daisy and I are gonna
就像五年前那样
start over just as if it were five years ago.
我不能对她要求太多
I wouldn't ask too much of her.
要求太多
Wouldn't ask too much?
不
No.
抱歉  老伙计  我很
I beg your pardon, old sport. It's just--
我很难过  因为很难使她
It's so sad, because it's so hard to make her
理解
understand.
很难使她理解
It's so hard to make her understand.
我为她建造了这一切
I've gotten all these things for her,
现在她居然想逃离
and now she just wants to run away.
她甚至想
She even wants
-逃离这些  -杰
- to leave that. - Jay.
你不能重复过去
You can't repeat the past.
不能重复过去
Can't repeat the past?
不
No.
为什么  你当然能
Why, of course you can.
你当然能
Of course you can.
我要把这些
I'm gonna fix things
修复得和过去一样
just the way they were before.
从那以后  一切都变得不对劲  我
Everything's been so confused since then. I
他滔滔不绝大谈往事
He talked a lot about the past
好似想要恢复什么
as if he wanted to recover something.
如果我能回到起点
If I could just get back to the start,
if I could just get back to the start
我能再次发现它
I could find it again.
他深爱着黛西的
Some vision
一些记忆
of himself that he had put into loving Daisy.
五年前  路易斯维尔的一个夜晚
One night in Louisville, five years ago
阴差阳错  盖茨比去了黛西家
Gatsby found himself at Daisy's house by colossal accident.
我去她家
I went to her house
是和泰勒营的其他军官一起去的
first with some of the officers from Camp Taylor.
我从未到过如此漂亮的房子
I'd never been in such a beautiful house.
一起跳下一支舞可以吗
May I save the next dance?
他的制服掩藏着
His uniform hid
一个事实
the truth that he was
他是个只有
a penniless young man
雄心壮志的
with only that
穷小子
grand vision of himself.
-黛西  别走  -我没有  母亲
- Daisy, don't scamper. - I was not, Mother.
这么多意气风发的年轻军官在这儿
So many dashing young officers here.
而且他们家世显赫
And from such illustrious families.
我知道我能往上爬
I always knew that I could climb.
但只能
But I could only climb
独自往上爬
if I climbed alone.
我知道
I knew
当我吻
that when I
这个姑娘的时候
kissed this girl
我就和她
I would be
永结连理了
forever wed to her.
于是我停下来
So I stopped.
我停下来
I stopped and I
等待
I waited.
等待了
I waited
一会儿
for a moment longer.
他知道
He knew
他的心灵再也不会像上帝的心灵一样
his mind would never again be free to romp like...
自由驰骋了
the mind of God.
坠入爱河
That falling in love
永远地改变了他的
would change his destiny
命运
forever.
然后我就放任了自己
And then I just let myself go.
她像花一样为他绽放
She blossomed for him like a flower
他们水乳交融
and the incarnation was complete.
我知道我这样的男人坠入爱河是天大的错
I knew it was a great mistake for a man like me to fall in love.
我才32岁  如果我能忘记失去过黛西
I'm only 32. I might still
我仍然可以成为一个了不起的人
be a great man if I could forget that I once
但是
lost Daisy, but
我的人生  老伙计  我的人生
my life, old sport, my life
我的人生必须这样
My life has got to be like this.
必须这么做
It's got to keep going up.
她得去找汤姆
She has to go to Tom
告诉他  她从未爱过他
and tell him that she never loved him.
我得给她多一点时间  老伙计
I just need to give her more time, old sport.
多一点时间
More time.
别担心  老伙计  别担心
Don't worry, old sport. Don't worry.
在这儿我能保护她
I can protect her here.
晚安  老伙计
Good night, old sport.
我能回到过去  老伙计
You're wrong about the past, old sport.
你错了
You're wrong.
从我邻居家里传来的音乐
There had been music from my neighbor's
持续了整个夏天
all summer.
在他的蓝色花园里  男男女女如飞蛾扑火般
In his blue gardens, men and girls came and went like moths
在星空下窃窃私语着  欢笑着
among the whisperings and the laughter and the stars.
早餐来了
Breakfast.
好的
Yes.
多谢  多谢
Thank you, thank you.
欢笑
Laughter.
多谢
Thank you.
不  是在星空下窃窃私语  喝着香槟
No. The whisperings and the champagne and the stars.
但是
But
派对宫殿暗夜到来
汤姆和黛西的来访之后
after Tom and Daisy's visit
盖茨比家的灯一盏一盏的熄了
Gatsby's lights went out one by one.
没有聚会了
There were no more parties.
黛西悄悄前来
Daisy visited discreetly.
杰·盖茨比这响亮的名头
For the very same fame that had all summer
虽曾让他满足
been a source of satisfaction to Jay Gatsby
现在却也成了威胁
had become a threat.
那神秘的女人是谁
我不想回家
I don't wanna go home.
我听说你辞退了所有佣人
I hear you fired all your servants.
黛西有时下午来
Daisy comes over sometimes in the afternoon.
我希望人们在我们决定怎么做之前
I wanted people who wouldn't
不要说长道短
gossip until we decide what we're going to do.
周边这些市镇
You see, these towns
非常紧密  老伙计
are very close together, old sport
上报纸很正常
and, well, it gets in the papers, you understand.
那些都是沃尔夫山姆想帮忙的人
They're all people Wolfshiem wanted to do something for.
只要他们会做饭会铺床叠被
What's the difference as long as they can cook
又有什么区别呢  是吧
and make beds, right?
尼克
Nick
黛西准备好了  她准备好了
Daisy's ready. She's ready.
还有一件事
There's just one thing.
她想邀请你和贝克小姐
She's requested that you and
明天去她家吃午饭
Miss Baker be there for lunch tomorrow at her house.
你会来吗  老伙计
Will you come, old sport?
黛西需要你
Daisy needs you.
我去
I'll.
我们需要你
We need you.
你能来吗  老伙计
Can you come, old sport?
我在哪里读到说
You know, I read somewhere
天气一年比一年热
that the sun is getting hotter every year.
等等
Wait a minute.
恰恰相反
It's the opposite.
天气一年比一年
Sun is getting colder
冷
every year.
今天我真想
Oh, I would like to be out
去海湾啊
on that bay today.
我住你对面
I'm right across from you.
那边
Right there.
果然是
So you are.
其实
You see
每一夜
every night
我都能看到
I can see
你码头尽头
that light
闪烁的灯
at the end of your dock blinking.
什么灯
What light?
布坎南先生
You see, Mr. Buchanan.
我想近一点
I wanted to be close.
-黛西和我都  -太热了
- Daisy and I have both-- - It's so hot!
一切都
Everything's
不对劲
so confused.
我们下午干什么
What'll we do this afternoon
明天干什么  后面30年干什么
or the day after that, or for the next 30 years?
发什么疯啊
Oh, don't be morbid.
我们进城去吧  谁想进城
Let's go to town. Who wants to go to town?
进城
Town?
女人总是有
Women get these
这些小心思
notions.
黛西
Daisy.
你看上去真帅
You look so cool.
你总是看上去那么帅
You always look so cool
就像时代广场
...like the advertisement
广告里的那个人
of the man in Times Square.
那个人穿着
The man
帅气漂亮的衬衫
in the cool, beautiful shirts.
她告诉盖茨比
She had told
她爱他
Gatsby that she loved him
而汤姆
and Tom
也都看到了
had seen.
我们进城去吧
Let's go to town.
求之不得呢
I'm perfectly willing.
真是个不错的主意
It's a marvelous idea.
亨利  备车
Henri! Have the car
马上开过来
brought around now.
我们不能
Can't anyone at least have
-先抽支烟吗  -午饭时抽过了
- a cigarette first? - We smoked through lunch.
别这样  找点儿乐子呗
Come on, let's have fun.
这么热  别闹了
It's too hot to fuss.
黛西  这是你提出来的呀
Daisy, it was your great idea.
咱们一起去城里吧
Why don't we? Let's all go to town.
我又改主意了  你个没良心的
I changed my mind, you brute.
去吧  在广场饭店开个大房间
Come on. We'll get a great big room at the Plaza,
喝着加冰威士忌  多享受啊
a bucket of ice, a bottle of whiskey, and it will be fun.
走吧
Come on.
这是你的主意呀
It was your idea.
随你便吧  汤姆
Fine. Have it your own way, Tom.
乔丹  咱们走
Come on, Jordan.
盖茨比先生  你也来吗
Will you join us, Mr. Gatsby?
两瓶威士忌  用毛巾包好
Two bottles of whiskey. Wrap them in a towel.
尼克  走啊
Come on, Nick!
盖茨比先生  你能开我的轿车吗
Mr. Gatsby, would you be good enough to take my coupe,
我用你的马戏团大篷车拉上其他人
and I'll drive everyone else in your circus wagon.
汽油恐怕不多了  老伙计
I don't think there's much gas, old sport.
汽油多得很
No, plenty of gas.
假如没油了  我可以找一个杂货店
Well, if I run out, I'll stop at a drugstore.
听说这年头杂货店什么都能买到
I hear you can buy anything at a drugstore nowadays.
你载着尼克和乔丹
You take Nick and Jordan.
-好啊  -咱们饭店见
- I suppose you can, yes. - We'll meet you at the Plaza.
我肯定比你们先到
I'll be the man on the corner smoking two cigarettes!
你们以为我是个蠢货  对吧
You must think I'm pretty dumb, don't you?
但我有种直觉  它会告诉我该怎么办
Well, I have a second sight sometimes that tells me what to do.
我小小的调查了一下这家伙
I've made a small investigation into this fellow.
你发现他上过牛津大学
And you found he was an Oxford man?
牛津  新墨西哥的牛津吧
Oxford, New Mexico.
就凭他那身粉色套装
He wears a pink suit, for christ's sake.
汤姆  咱们快没油了
Tom, we're almost out of gas.
威尔逊
Wilson!
还等什么呢
What are you waiting for?
快给我加点油
Let's have some gas!
还要我自己动手吗
Do I have to do it myself?
你以为我是来看风景的吗
You think I come here to admire the view?
-不好意思  我病了  -为什么
- I'm sorry, I'm sick. - Why?
-怎么回事  -我也不知道
- Why, what's the matter? - I don't know.
我感觉很虚弱
I'm all run down.
-我需要钱  非常需要  -啥
- I need money real bad. - What?
我和我老婆要去西部了
My wife and I, we wanna go West.
你老婆也想去吗
Your wife does?
汤姆感到心乱如麻
Tom was feeling the hot whips of panic.
一小时前还尽在掌握的情妇和夫人
His mistress and wife an hour ago so secure
却都要离他而去
were both slipping from his control.
这两天我想通了一些有趣的事情
I wised up to something funny these last two days.
不管她愿不愿意  她都要去
Yeah, she's going West whether she wants to or not.
我欠你多少钱
What do I owe you?
一块钱  一块二
A dollar. A dollar and twenty.
我把那车给你了
You can have the car.
明天我就送过来
I'll send it over tomorrow!
好了  好了
Okay, fine, fine, fine.
再开一扇窗户吧
Open another window.
没有别的窗户了
There aren't any more.
要把斧头自己砍一个
Then telephone for an ax.
心静自然凉
Will you forget about the heat?
你这样唠叨只会更热
You make it worse by crabbing about it.
何不由着她来呢  老伙计
Why not let her alone, old sport?
这是你的口头禅吗
That's a great expression of yours, isn't it?
什么
What is?
老伙计
"Old sport."
你在哪学的
Where'd you pick it up?
汤姆  如果你想要人身攻击
See here, Tom. If you're going to make personal remarks,
我马上就走
I won't stay here a minute.
盖茨比先生  听说你是牛津毕业生
Mr. Gatsby, I understand that you're an Oxford man.
不  不完全是
No, not exactly, no.
我知道你念过牛津
Oh, yes, I understand that you went to Oxford.
是的  我念过
Well, yes, I went there.
-这粉衣男居然还念过牛津  -汤姆
- Sure. The man in the pink suit went to Oxford. - Tom.
我说了我念过
I said I went there, didn't I?
我听到了
Oh, I heard you.
我想知道是什么时候
I'd like to know when.
你想知道是什么时候对吗
You'd like to know when.
说呀  盖茨比先生
Well, Mr. Gatsby?
那是1919年  我在那只待了五个月
It was in 1919. I only stayed there five months.
所以我不自称牛津毕业生
That's why I can't exactly call myself an Oxford man.
他们为一些参战军官
You see, it was an opportunity they gave to some of us officers
提供了就读的机会
who fought in the war.
我真想过去给他鼓鼓劲
I wanted to get up and slap Gatsby on the back.
我给你调杯酒吧  汤姆
I'll make you a drink, Tom.
这样你就不会显得这么蠢
Then you won't seem so stupid to yourself.
等等
Wait a minute.
我还要问盖茨比先生一个问题
I want to ask Mr. Gatsby one more question.
请便  布坎南先生
Oh, please, please, go on, Mr. Buchanan. Go on.
你想在我家闹多大的事
What kind of a row are you trying to cause in my house anyhow?
他没有闹事  是你在闹事
He isn't causing a row, you're causing a row.
管好你自己吧
Please have a little self-control.
管好我自己
Self-control?
是不是现在流行装聋作哑
Oh, I suppose the latest thing is to sit back
任由不知道从哪出来的阿猫阿狗
and let Mr. Nobody From Nowhere
跟你老婆上床
make love to your wife.
你要是想谈这个  那我失陪了
Well, if that's the idea you can count me out.
开始人们对家庭生活和家庭制度
See, nowadays people begin by sneering
嗤之以鼻
at family life and family institutions
接下来他们就该把所有传统抛之脑后
and the next you'll know, we'll throw everything overboard,
要黑白通婚了
we'll have intermarriage between black and white!
你老婆并不爱你
Your wife doesn't love you.
她从来没爱过你
She never loved you.
她爱的是我
You see, she loves me.
你疯了吧
You must be crazy.
没有  老伙计
No, old sport.
她从没爱过你
No, you see, she never loved you.
她嫁给你只是因为我很穷
She only married you because I was poor
而她等不下去了
and she was tired of waiting.
嫁给你是个大错误  可在她心中
It was a terrible terrible mistake, but in her heart,
她从未爱过别人
in her heart, she never loved anyone but me.
-我们走吧  -都回家吧
- We should go. - Let's all go home.
黛西  坐下
Sit down, Daisy!
别这样  坐下好吗
Please. Please, take a seat.
坐吧  黛西
Go on, Daisy.
黛西  这是怎么回事
Daisy, what's been going on?
-我要听来龙去脉  -我告诉过你了
- I want to hear about it. - I told you what's going on.
我们之间已经五年了
It's been going on for five years.
你和这家伙交往五年了
You've been seeing him for five years?
不  没有交往  我们见不了面
No, no, no, not seeing. Not seeing, we couldn't.
但这五年我们一直深爱着对方
But both of us loved each other all that time. Didn't we?
就这呀
Oh, that's all.
你真是疯了
You're crazy!
我说不好五年前的事
I can't speak about what happened five years ago
因为那时我还不认识黛西
because I didn't know Daisy then.
我也想不通你是怎么接近她的
And I'll be damned if I see how you got within a mile of her
除非你是杂货店送货的
unless you brought the groceries to the back door.
至于你其它的话都是扯淡
But all the rest of that is a goddamn lie.
黛西嫁给我时就爱着我
Daisy loved me when she married me,
现在也是
and she loves me now.
不  很抱歉  布坎南先生
No. No. I'm sorry, Mr. Buchanan.
-她不爱你  -她爱我
- No. - She does! She does, though.
她仍然爱我
No, she does, though.
她爱我  而我也爱着她
She does. And what's more, I love Daisy too.
我爱你  黛西
No. I love you, Daisy.
有时我会做些荒唐事  可我总会回头
Now, once in a while I go off on a spree. I always come back.
-荒唐事  -我心底里一直爱着她
- A spree. - And in my heart I love her all the time.
你真令人作呕
You're revolting.
知道我们为什么离开芝加哥吗
You know why we left Chicago?
他们竟然没有告诉你
I'm surprised they didn't treat you
他干的那点儿荒唐事
to the story of that little spree!
那一切都结束了  黛西
That's all over now, Daisy, darling. That's all over.
告诉他实情
Just tell him the truth. Go on.
告诉他你从未爱过他
That you never loved him
过去的一切就一笔勾销了
and this will all be wiped out forever.
我怎么可能爱他
How could I love him possibly?
别忘了咱们的计划
Remember our plans.
告诉他你从未爱过他
You tell him that you never loved him
所有这些痛苦就成为过眼云烟了
and all this pain will be wiped out forever.
黛西
Daisy.
黛西  告诉他
Daisy, tell him.
我从没爱过他
I never loved him.
从没有吗
Never?
-没有  -没有
- No. - No.
在夏威夷凯皮奥兰尼也没有吗
Not at Kapiolani?
我怕你打湿鞋  把你从游艇上抱下来
Not that day I carried you down from the Punch Bowl
你也没爱过我吗
to keep your shoes dry?
没有过吗
Never?
请别说了
Please don't.
黛西
Daisy.
杰
There, Jay.
你的要求太过分了
You want too much.
我现在爱你  难道这还不够吗
I love you now. Isn't that enough?
过去的事我无法挽回
I can't help what's past.
我确实曾经爱过他  但我也爱过你啊
I did love him once, but I loved you too.
你也爱过我
You loved me too?
你也爱我
You loved me...?
连这也是谎话
Even that is a lie!
她根本不知道你还活着
She didn't know you were alive!
黛西和我之间有些事
There are things between Daisy and me, Gatsby,
你永远也不会知道
that you'll never know.
我们两个永远也不会忘记
Things that neither of us can ever forget.
我要单独和黛西谈谈
I need to speak to Daisy alone.
她被你弄得太激动了  老伙计
You see, you've got her all excited now, don't you, old sport?
黛西
Daisy.
就算单独谈我也不能说从未爱过汤姆
Even alone I can't say I never loved Tom.
那不是真心话
It wouldn't be true.
-什么  -当然不是真心话
- What? - Of course it wouldn't.
-好像你还在乎似的  -当然在乎了
- As if it mattered to you. - Of course it matters!
从今天起我要更好的照顾你
I'm gonna take better care of you from now on.
你没机会再照顾她了  她要离开你了
You're not taking care of Daisy anymore. She's leaving you.
胡扯
Nonsense!
-我的确要离开你  -别  别
- I am, though! - No, no, no.
她不会离开我的
She is not leaving me.
肯定不会为了像你这样的江湖骗子离开我
Certainly not for a common swindler like you.
盖茨比先生  你到底是谁
Mr. Gatsby, exactly who are you, anyhow?
我调查了一下你
I made an investigation into your affairs.
你是跟迈耶·沃尔夫山姆一起的
You're one of Meyer Wolfshiem's bunch.
求你了  咱们回家吧
Please, let's go home.
他和沃尔夫山姆这家伙买下了很多杂货店
See, he and this Wolfshiem, they bought up drugstores.
暗地里贩卖私酒
And sold bootlegged alcohol over the counter.
那又怎样呢  老伙计
What about it, old sport?
别叫我老伙计
Don't you call me "Old sport."
这杂货店生意还只是
And this drugstore business is just small change
他和沃尔夫山姆耍的
compared to this bonds stunt
许多小把戏之一呢
that you and Wolfshiem have got going.
你的朋友沃尔特·切斯可不觉得和我们合伙丢人
Your friend Walter Chase isn't too proud to come in?
我想过这个问题
I gave that some thought.
像沃尔特·切斯这样久负盛名的银行家
How does a reputable banker like Walter Chase
是怎样欠沃尔夫山姆这样的小卒
find himselfup to his eyeballs in debt.
-我来告诉你  -一屁股债的呢
- I'll tell you. - to a little kike like Wolfshiem?
-因为贪婪  老伙计  -没错
- It's called greed, old sport. - That's right!
你还把半个华尔街的人都请到
And you have half of Wall Street out there swilling your
你每个周末的免费酒会上
free booze at that fun park every weekend.
他竟然没想拉你下水吗
I'm surprised he hasn't tried to drag you in.
天哪  他还真这么干了
My God, he has.
他跟这没关系...
He's got nothing to do with...
跟你花天酒地的生活吗
With your little racket.
黛西
Daisy.
这个人有大房子  酒会和光鲜的衣服
Can't you see who this guy is
你就看不清他的真面目了吗
with his house and his parties and his fancy clothes?
他只不过是沃尔夫山姆的马前卒
He is just a front for Wolfshiem,
引诱沃尔特·切斯这样的上流人士上钩的小弟
a gangster to get his claws into respectable folk like Walter Chase.
老伙计  你身上唯一上流的东西是你的钱
The only respectable thing about you, old sport, is your money.
仅此而已  而我的钱和你不相上下
Your money, that's it. Now I've just as much as you.
我们平起平坐
That means we're equal.
不  不
Oh, no. No.
我们大相径庭
We're different.
我
I am.
他们
They are.
她
She is.
我们都和你不一样
We're all different from you.
我们出身不一样
You see, we were born different.
我们流淌的血液不同
It's in our blood
无论你做什么说什么  哪怕你去偷
and nothing that you do or say or steal
我们都是你做梦也无法企及的
or dream up can ever change that.
像黛西这样的女孩...
A girl like Daisy...
你给我闭嘴
You shut up!
别说了
Shut up!
给我闭嘴  闭嘴
You shut up! Shut up!
闭上你的嘴
Shut up!
那一刻  盖茨比看上去
Gatsby looked, in that moment
仿佛刚刚杀了个人
as if he had killed a man.
我诚恳地...
My sincerest...
诚恳地表示歉意
My sincerest apologies.
我没控制好自己的脾气
I seem to have lost my temper.
这就对了  盖茨比先生
That's right, Mr. Gatsby.
瞧瞧你在牛津学的礼节
Show us some of those fine Oxford manners.
黛西  亲爱的
Daisy, darling.
没事的  别介意
None of this has any consequence.
黛西
Daisy.
黛西  说话呀  亲爱的
Daisy, talk to me, darling.
我刚才失控了  仅此而已
I just lost my temper, that's all.
他开始情绪激动地讲话
He began talking excitedly,
可每一句话
but with every word
都让黛西越来越想离开这一切
Daisy was drawing further and further into herself.
...去你父母在路易斯维尔的家
...to go to your parents' house in Louisville.
求你了  汤姆  我再也受不了了
Please, Tom, I can't stand it anymore!
你们两个坐盖茨比先生的车回家吧
Why don't you two start on home in Mr. Gatsby's car.
-黛西  亲爱的  看着我  -走吧
- Daisy, darling, look at me. - Go on.
黛西
Daisy.
他不会烦你的
He won't annoy you.
他应该知道调情到此为止了
I think he realizes that this little flirtation is over.
黛西 黛西
Daisy? Daisy!
还喝吗
You want any of this?
乔丹
Jordan?
尼克
Nick?
Nick.
什么
What?
来点儿吗
You want any?
不了
No.
我刚想起来今天是我生日
I just remembered today's my birthday.
生日快乐
Happy birthday.
三十岁了  又一个孤独的十年
Thirty. The promise of a decade of loneliness.
三十而立的惊喜逐渐消失
The formidable stroke of 30 died away
就像盖茨比和黛西在渐渐凉爽的暮色中
as Gatsby and Daisy drove on through the cooling twilight
驶向死亡
towards death.
别跟我撒谎
Don't you lie to me!
你从哪弄来的这个
Hey, where'd you get these from?
你也许能愚弄我  但你骗不过上帝
You might fool me, but you don't fool God!
上帝无所不知
God sees everything!
桃金娘
Myrtle!
你去哪了
Where are you?
是汤姆吗
Tom?
汤姆
Tom!
桃金娘
Myrtle!
我在这儿  停下
I'm here! Stop!
宝贝
Baby!
汤姆
Tom!
等等
Wait!
慢点儿开
Slow down.
慢点
Slow down!
前方有重大交通事故
Bad trouble up ahead, sir!
不错  威尔逊总算能有点生意了
Good. Wilson'll have a little business at last.
过去看看
Let's take a look.
不去不行吗
Oh, must we?
就看一眼
Just a look.
走吧
Come on.
往后站  把这让出来
Move back! Clear the space here!
尊重一下死者
Have a little respect!
如果没有正当理由进入楼内
If you don't have a legitimate reason to be in the building,
就待在外面
I want you outside!
如果你是今晚事故的目击者
If you saw anything tonight you'd like to talk to me about,
请在外面告诉我
well, then you can talk to me outside.
不要进去  懂吗
I don't want you in here. Okay?
请靠后站
Please. Stand back. Please.
我的上帝啊
My God.
好了  伙计们
All right, folks.
让一让  让一让
Make some room, huh? Make some room back there!
跟你没关系就让开
If you have no business, clear out!
这位先生  你在干嘛
Sir. What are you doing? Sir!
先生  请你...
Sir, I'm asking you...
别碰我
Get off me!
我没事
I'm fine.
我很好
你认识她对吗
You knew her?
不  不认识
Not really. No.
那就请过来吧  先生
I gotta ask you to step back, sir.
出了什么事
So, what happened?
她冲到了马路中间
She ran out in the road.
那个狗娘养的连车都没停
Son of a bitch didn't even stop his car.
我看到了  是一辆黄色的车
I saw it. It was a yellow car.
一辆大黄车
A big yellow car.
不知道从哪冲出来的
Damn thing came out of nowhere.
是的  黄色的大杜森堡  定做的
Yeah. Yeah, a big yellow Duesy. Custom job.
美国经典豪华车
不用告诉我是什么车
You don't have to tell me what kind of car it was.
我知道是什么车
I know what kind of car it was.
威尔逊
Wilson.
-振作点儿  -我知道是什么车
- Just pull yourself together! - I know what kind of car it was!
他太伤心了  大家都出去吧
He's upset! Everybody out!
不知道他需要安静吗
Can't you see the man needs peace and quiet?
威尔逊  我刚从纽约回来
Wilson! I just got here from New York.
别这样  威尔逊
No! Hey! Wilson!
我把轿车给你开来了
I was bringing you the coupe.
坐下  坐下
Sit down! Sit down.
给他点儿水  喝点儿水
Get him a drink. Get him a drink.
那辆黄车不是我的
That yellow car wasn't mine!
听见了吗  我一下午都没见过了
You hear? I haven't seen it all afternoon.
你的车是什么颜色
What color's your car?
蓝的
It's blue.
轿车
Coupe.
我们刚从纽约过来
We just got here from New York.
他们刚来
They just stopped!
知道了
OK.
蓝车
Blue.
对
Right.
给我
Here.
我俩单独待会儿
Leave us alone.
威尔逊
Wilson.
那辆黄车是谁的
Who owns the yellow car?
一个叫盖茨比的人的
A fella named Gatsby.
杰·盖茨比
Jay Gatsby.
他是个骗子  乔治
He's a crook, George.
报纸上的宴会就是他举办的
Yes. Throws those parties the papers are always talking about.
没准就是他勾引的桃金娘
Maybe he was the one that was fooling around with Myrtle.
也许就是因为这他才杀了她
Maybe that's why he killed her.
是啊  也许吧
Yeah, maybe.
像他这样的人  谁知道呢
Guy like that, who knows?
那也没必要杀了她
He didn't have to kill her.
盖茨比
Gatsby.
这种人要遭天谴的
Something ought to be done about a fella like that.
他会遭报应的
He'll pay.
血债血偿
Oh, he'll pay.
懦夫
Coward.
连车都没停
He didn't even stop his car.
你还要为他说话吗
You gonna defend him now?
我去叫辆出租  尼克
I'll telephone for a taxi, Nick.
进来边吃晚饭边等吧
Why don't you come inside and have some supper while you wait?
不  谢了  我在外面等
No, thanks. I'll wait outside.
你什么毛病
What is the matter with you?
你不进来吗  尼克
Won't you come in, Nick?
不了  谢谢
No, thanks.
这才九点半
It's only half past 9.
不了  我受够了
No, I've had enough.
受够了你们所有人
Of everyone.
老伙计
Hello, old sport.
你干嘛呢
What are you doing?
在这儿坐坐
Just sitting here.
是  我看到了
Yes, I see that.
你在路上看见什么了吗
You see any trouble out on the road?
你撞的那个女人已经死了  杰
That woman you ran down is dead, Jay.
我猜也是
I thought so.
我对黛西也是这么说的
I told Daisy that I thought so.
黛西  你说的是什么啊
Daisy? Do you hear yourself?
你怎么能这样
How could you?
你怎么能这样做
How could you do that?
-小点儿声  -你怎么回事
- Keep your voice down. -What's wrong with you?
你就是个懦夫
You're nothing but a goddamn coward!
小点儿声
Keep your voice down!
别吵吵  当时没必要停车...
Please. There was no point in stop...
怎么没必要  那个女人怎么办
No point'? No point? What about that woman?
没必要  她当时就被撞死了
No point. She was killed instantly.
没错  都开膛破肚了
Yes, it ripped her open!
我去过那  看到她了
I was there! I saw her!
我明白  我明白是我的错
I understand! I understand! It was my fault.
是我的错
It was my fault.
那个女人朝我们直冲过来
This woman, she rushed out at us
好像想和我们说话
as if she was trying to speak to us.
一切发生的都太快了
It all happened so quickly.
-她...  我想扳过方向盘  -她
- She tried... I tried to turn in time... -"She"?
可是
but...
是黛西撞的人
It was Daisy.
离开纽约后  她精神非常紧张
You see, after we left New York, she was very nervous.
她觉得开车可以舒缓心情
She thought that driving would steady her.
而这个女人却向我们扑来
But this woman, she rushed out at us.
事情发生的太快了
It all happened so quickly.
这不是她的错  明白吗
It wasn't her fault, do you see?
黛西开车的事绝不能有任何人知道
No one must know that Daisy was driving.
答应我
Promise me.
杰  你得回家休息休息
Jay, you should go home and get some rest.
我要在这儿等着
I'm going to wait here.
如果有必要  就等一整夜
I'm going to wait here all night if necessary.
别这样  这样不好
No, no, no. That's not a good idea.
如果他敢因为下午的不愉快
If he tries to bother her
而找她麻烦
about that unpleasantness this afternoon,
如果他敢打搅她
If he tries to bother her,
如果他敢对她乱来的话...
If he tries any brutality on her whatsoever...
汤姆不会碰她的  他现在想的不是她
Tom won't touch her. He's not even thinking about her.
我不相信他
I don't trust him.
-我信不过他  -好吧
- I don't trust him. - All right.
好吧
All right.
你在这等着
You wait here.
我去看看有什么情况
I'll see if there's any commotion.
真的吗
Would you?
谢谢  老伙计
Thank you, old sport.
是她的错  是她自己跑到马路上的
Listen, she was in the wrong, running out on the road.
亲爱的  不用担心
Sweetheart, you have nothing to worry about.
交给我来处理
Let me take care of things.
让我来照顾你
Take care of you.
我去打几个电话
I'll make some calls.
然后我们就离开
We'll go away.
离开这城市
Just go away, get out of town.
你休息一下  别担心
Get some rest. Don't worry.
没事的
It'll be all right.
你好  老伙计
Oh. Hello, old sport.
杰
Jay.
-一切都还好吧  -是的
- Everything all right? - Yes.
一切都还好
Everything's just fine.
凌晨4点的时候  她来到窗前
Four o'clock, she... she came to the window.
就站在那
She stood there, then...
然后把灯关掉了
She turned out the light, so...
来帮帮忙  好吧  老伙计
Give me a hand, will you, old sport?
我本该告诉他我刚见到的  但是
I should have told him what I had just seen, but...
说出口的却是
All I could manage was:
杰  发生了这些事
You know, Jay, with everything that's happened,
你应该离开
you ought to go away.
就今晚  他们会追踪你的车
Tonight. They'll trace your car.
离开  不  现在我不能离开
Go away? No, I can't leave now.
起码不是今晚
Not tonight.
杰  你知道死人了吗
Jay, do you understand that a woman has been killed?
黛西会在早上打给我
Daisy's going to call in the morning.
之后我们计划一起离开
Then we'll make plans to go away together.
-没错  -黛西她...
- Yeah. - Daisy, she...
她只是需要时间想清楚  赫佐格
She just needs time to think things through. Herzog.
我们有话要说  谢谢
We're talking. Thank you.
她只是需要时间想想
She just needs time to think.
不  杰  黛西她...
No, Jay. With Daisy...
她只是需要时间想想  早上她会打来的
She just needs time to think. She's going to call in the morning.
跟我一起等吧
Wait up with me.
太阳快要升起了
The sun's almost up.
终于在那晚  他把一切都告诉了我
That was the night he finally told me the truth.
毫无保留
All of it.
我曾经觉得
You know, I've thought for a while,
我拥有很多  但其实我一无所有
I had a lot of things, but the truth is I'm empty.
我想这就是我要说谎的原因
I suppose that's why I make things up about myself.
但很早以前我就想告诉你整件事
But I've wanted to tell you the whole story for a very long time.
我出身贫寒  老伙计
See, I grew up terribly, terribly poor, old sport.
我的家人...
My folks were...
他透露了他卑微的出身
He revealed his humble beginnings,
与丹·科迪改变命运的航行
his transformative voyage with Dan Cody,
战争  牛津大学
the war, Oxford,
还有他是如何加入沃尔夫山姆的生意当中
and how he joined Wolfshiem in the business.
也是在那一晚
It was also that night,
我意识到盖茨比天生非常乐观
that I became aware of Gatsby's extraordinary gift for hope.
我无法形容
I can't describe
发现自己爱上她时感到多诧异
how surprised I was to find out that I loved her.
而且她也爱我
And that she loved me too.
我从未见过谁天生就这么乐观
A gift that I have never found in any other person.
没想到还有这么好的女孩
I never realized how extraordinary a nice girl could be.
我觉得也不再会有了
And which it is not likely I shall ever find again.
我在想有了黛西以后的生活
I thought out my life with Daisy in it,
想怎样才能跟她结婚
trying to figure out how we could marry
才能负担起每月庞大的开销
and struggle along on so many dollars a month.
信中说了什么
What was in the letter?
为什么战后我不能回去
The reason why after the war I hadn't been able to return.
我让她等我  等我有所成就
I asked her to wait until I made something of myself,
但她却...
but she was...
我觉得已经和她永结连理了
See, I felt married to her.
就是这样
That was all.
一切都是为了她
It was all for her.
房子  派对
The house, the parties.
所有的一切
Everything.
一切尽在上帝眼里
God sees everything.
盖茨比先生  很抱歉
Mr. Gatsby, sir, excuse me.
芝加哥来电  先生
Chicago calling, sir.
现在不是时候
Not now.
待会我再打过去
Keep it open for a personal call.
再打过去  好的
A personal call? Of course.
抱歉  盖茨比先生  我准备今天清池子
Excuse me, sir. Mr. Gatsby, I'm gonna drain the pool today,
趁着叶子还没落
before the leaves start falling in.
今天不行
Not today.
今天不行  真漂亮
Not today, it's so beautiful.
老伙计  我整个夏天都没下过泳池
You know, old sport, I haven't used that pool once all summer.
我们去游个泳吧
Let's take a swim.
把电话放到泳池边
Have the phone brought down to the pool.
我得走了  杰
I have to go, Jay.
我得去上班了
I have to work.
好吧
I understand.
我送你出去
I'll walk you out.
我会打给你的
Well, I'll call you up.
一言为定  老伙计  一言为定
Please do, old sport. Please do.
我想黛西也会打来的
I supposed that Daisy will call too.
我...我想也是
I... I suppose.
是啊
Yes.
再见
Well, goodbye.
杰
Jay!
现在人们都腐朽至极
They're a rotten crowd.
他们加起来也比不上你一个
You're worth the whole damn bunch put together.
我很高兴我说了出来
I was always glad I said that.
因为我只称赞过他那么一次
It was the only compliment I ever paid him.
那天早晨
That morning,
华尔街仍旧欣欣向荣
Wall Street boomed its usual golden roar.
但我一点工作的心思也没有
But I wasn't worth a decent stroke of work.
我在等盖茨比打来告诉我消息
I waited for Gatsby to call with news.
当他在等黛西电话时...
While he waited for Daisy...
盖茨比宅邸
Gatsby's.
盖茨比先生很高兴你打过来
I know Mr. Gatsby will be very happy that you've called.
黛西
Daisy.
喂  喂
Hello! Hello!
喂  一切都还好吗
Hello! Is everything all right?
喂  喂
Hello! Hello!
喂
Hello!
喂  一切都还好吗
Hello! Is everything all right?
我还记得那天余下的时间
I remember the rest of that day
充斥着络绎不绝的警察
as an endless drill of police
摄影师和小报记者
and photographers and tabloid reporters.
新闻头条简直是一场噩梦
The headlines were a nightmare.
贩卖私酒者怒杀情妇
他们把责任都推到盖茨比头上
They pinned everything on Gatsby.
与桃金娘的私情  肇事逃逸
The affair with Myrtle. The hit-and-run.
肇事逃逸
盖茨比畏罪自杀
所有的一切
Everything.
我又能说什么呢
And there was nothing I could say,
除了一切都是假的这个难言的事实以外
except the one unutterable fact that none of it was true.
亲爱的  爸爸正在照顾着
Darling, Daddy's taking care of
他最爱的两个姑娘
his two favorite girls.
我们要去哪
Where are we going?
-去度假  -该走了
- We're going on a holiday. - We should go.
只有你和我  还有爸爸
Just you me and Daddy.
布坎南宅邸
Buchanan residence.
我找布坎南夫人
May I speak to Mrs. Buchanan?
我是卡罗威先生  她的表弟
It's Mr. Carraway, her cousin.
夫人她没空  卡罗威先生
Madame is not available, Monsieur Carraway.
要是碰到她  告诉她葬礼在明天
If you speak to her, tell her the funeral's tomorrow.
很抱歉  先生  他们已经走了
I'm sorry, monsieur, they have gone away.
走了
Gone away?
你知道他们什么时候回来吗
Do you know when they'll be back?
不知道
No.
他们已经离开了
They have already departed.
求你了  她肯定想出席的  她...
Please. I know that she would want to be there. She would...
只要你告诉她就可以了
If you would just get a message to her.
-让我跟她说  求你了  -你想找她
- Let me talk to her, please. - You wish to contact her?
我也不知道她去了哪  先生
I have no further information, monsieur.
求你了
Please!
再见
Au revoir.
喂
Hello?
走吧
Come on.
他们都是冷漠的人  汤姆跟黛西
They were careless people, Tom and Daisy.
他们出来闹个天翻地覆
They smashed up things and people
再退到他们的钱
and then retreated back into their money
和冷漠筑成的围城
and their vast carelessness.
快滚出去
Hey! Get out of here!
出去
Go on!
快给我滚出去
Get the hell out of here!
我打电话
I rang,
写信
I wrote,
苦苦哀求
I implored.
但受过他款待的人
But not a single one of the sparkling hundreds
没一个来参加他的葬礼
that enjoyed his hospitality attended the funeral.
至于黛西
And from Daisy,
连朵花都没送
not even a flower.
我就是他的所有
I was all he had.
唯一还关心他的人
The only one who cared.
盖茨比死后
After Gatsby's death,
纽约一直萦绕着我
New York was haunted for me.
这座城市
That city,
我曾憧憬着熠熠生辉的海市蜃楼
my once golden shimmering mirage,
如今竟让我感到恶心
now made me sick.
在纽约的最后一晚
On my last night in New York,
我再次回到那座庞大杂乱的房子
I returned to that huge incoherent house once more.
沃尔夫山姆的伙伴已把这清空
Wolfshiem's associates had cleaned it out.
他办那么多的派对只为她一晚的出现
He threw all those parties hoping she'd wander in one night.
这就像个游乐园
It's like an amusement park.
但你一个人怎么住呢
But how do you live here all alone?
她让一切都熠熠生辉
She makes it look so splendid.
不是吗  老伙计
Don't you think, old sport?
音乐  这样我们就可以彻夜狂舞了
Music! And then we can dance all night!
你会来吗  老伙计
Will you come, old sport?
我们需要你
We need you.
真希望一直这样
I wish it could always be like this.
会的
It will be.
我还记得我们是如何齐聚在盖茨比家
I remembered how we had all come to Gatsby's
猜测他如何腐败
and guessed at his corruption.
而他就站在我们面前
While he stood before us,
心中纯洁无比
concealing an incorruptible dream.
很完美  出自你完美的  不可抗拒的想象力
It's perfect. From your perfect, irresistible imagination.
月亮渐渐升起
The moon rose higher.
当我站在那
And as I stood there,
怀缅这个古老而又未知的世界时
brooding on the old, unknown world,
我想到了盖茨比
I thought of Gatsby's wonder,
第一次在黛西家的码头尽头
when he first picked out the green light
看到绿光时的惊喜
at the end of Daisy's dock.
他历尽漫长的艰辛
He had come such a long way.
想必梦想已经触手可及
And his dream must have seemed so close,
几乎不可能失手
that he could hardly fail to grasp it.
但他却不知道其实梦想早已落在他身后
But he did not know that it was already behind him.
盖茨比信奉这盏绿灯
Gatsby believed in the green light,
快乐与我们渐行渐远
the orgastic future that year by year recedes before us.
它逃避我们  不过没关系
It eluded us then, but that's no matter.
明天  我们将跑得更快
Tomorrow, we will run faster,
手臂将伸得更远
stretch out our arms farther.
在一个晴朗的早晨
And one fine morning,
我们努力向前划
So we beat on,
逆流而上的小舟
boats against the current,
不停地
borne back,
被浪潮
ceaselessly,
推回过去
into the past.
《盖茨比》  尼克·卡罗威著
《了不起的盖茨比》